<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Life after death Containing many religious instructions and godly exhortations, for all those that meane to liue holy, and dye blessedly. With the manner of disposing ones selfe to God, before, and at the time of his departure out of this world. With many prayers for the same purpose By Francis Rodes.</title>
            <author>Rodes, Francis, Sir, ca. 1595-1646.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1622</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 127 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 114 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10874</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21140</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S112044</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99847303</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99847303</idno>
            <idno type="VID">12333</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10874)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 12333)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1581:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Life after death Containing many religious instructions and godly exhortations, for all those that meane to liue holy, and dye blessedly. With the manner of disposing ones selfe to God, before, and at the time of his departure out of this world. With many prayers for the same purpose By Francis Rodes.</title>
                  <author>Rodes, Francis, Sir, ca. 1595-1646.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 208, 207-216 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by G. Purslowe] for Thomas Dewe, in St. Dunstanes Churchyard in Fleetstreet,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1622.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Pages 207-08 repeated in number only; text continuous despite pagination.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Death --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-04</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:12333:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12333:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>LIFE AFTER DEATH.</p>
            <p>CONTAINING many religious inſtructions and godly exhortations, for all thoſe that meane to liue holy, and dye <hi>bleſſedly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>With the manner of diſpoſing ones ſelfe to God, before, and at the time of his departure out of this world.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>With many Prayers for the</hi> ſame purpoſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> FRANCIS RODES.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for THOMAS DEVVE, in S<hi rend="sup">t</hi> 
               <hi>Dunſtanes</hi> Churchyard in Fleetſtreet. 1622.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:12333:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:12333:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is a common cuſtome, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treat fauour from courteous Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. If the matter bee good, or the men courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, the ſuite of fauour will bee eaſily granted: if otherwiſe, it is but a needleſſe ſhame, to beg a commendation, where
<pb facs="tcp:12333:3"/>
none is deſerued. And therefore I leaue to eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man the libertie of his iudgement, and doe expoſe this Tract to ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall cenſure.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>F.R.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:12333:3"/>
            <head>A Table of the chiefe points contained in this Treatiſe.</head>
            <list>
               <label>CHAP. 1.</label>
               <item>THE ſeuerall ſorts of Death.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 2</label>
               <item>To learne to die well, ought to bee the chiefe ſtudy of our life.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 3</label>
               <item>Why men do ſo ſeldome enter into a ſerious remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of their end.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 4</label>
               <item>The neceſsity of our continuall meditating vpon Death.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 5.</label>
               <item>Neceſſary obſeruations in our meditating of Death.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 6.</label>
               <item>Againſt the feare of Death.</item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12333:4"/>
                  <hi>CHAP. 7</hi>
               </label>
               <item>How to carry our ſelues concerning Death.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 8</label>
               <item>This life is but a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, a pilgrimage, &amp;c.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 9</label>
               <item>The vulgar remedy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst Death.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 10</label>
               <item>Grieuances and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſes of fearfull men to couer their complaints of Death.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 11</label>
               <item>How Death is to bee deſired.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 12</label>
               <item>The miſerable ſtate and condition of this preſent life.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 13</label>
               <item>Againſt the loue of the world.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 14</label>
               <item>Againſt procraſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 15</label>
               <item>Againſt miſtruſt in Gods mercy.</item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12333:4"/>
                  <hi>CHAP. 16</hi>
               </label>
               <item>Gods promiſes to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that repent, are mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold, abſolute, &amp; vniuerſall.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 17</label>
               <item>How one ſhould de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meane himſelfe when ſicknes beginneth.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 18</label>
               <item>How the ſicke ſhould diſpoſe his worldly goods.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 19</label>
               <item>How hee is to apply himſelfe to Prayer and Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditation.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 20</label>
               <item>Whom the duty of vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiting the ſicke, ſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 21</label>
               <item>A Prayer at the firſt viſiting of the Sicke.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 22</label>
               <item>A confeſsion to be v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed of the ſicke by himſelfe.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 23</label>
               <item>A Prayer of the ſick par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty againſt the feare of death.</item>
               <label>
                  <pb facs="tcp:12333:5"/>
                  <hi>CHAP. 24</hi>
               </label>
               <item>A Prayer for the ſick.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 25</label>
               <item>A forme of leauing the ſicke to Gods protection.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 26</label>
               <item>The manner of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mending the ſicke, into the hands of God, at the houre of Death.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 27</label>
               <item>A Prayer for the ſick, at his departing out of this life.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 28</label>
               <item>The bleſsing of the ſicke, when hee is giuing vp the ghoſt.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 29</label>
               <item>A Prayer to bee vſed by the aſſembly, after the ſicke party departed.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 30</label>
               <item>Conſolation againſt immoderate griefe for the loſſe of friends.</item>
               <label>CHAP. 31</label>
               <item>The cuſtom of Funerals.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:12333:5"/>
            <head>A TREATISE OF LIFE AND DEATH.</head>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here are three ſorts of Death: The firſt is, a dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in ſinne: that is,<note place="margin">1. Dying in Sinne.</note> when we doe giue our ſelues o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer to the delights and pleaſures of this life; and
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:12333:6"/>
doe neuer think of death, till it comes: and when it is come, wee doe then re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coyle and draw back, as beeing vnwilling to dye: thereby making our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture vnhappy; becauſe none dyes well, that dies vnwillingly: neither can any hope for Heauen, that approches thereunto, on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by compulſion.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2. Dying to ſinne.</note>The ſecond is, a dying to Sin, that is, when our ſins die before our ſelues; namely, when wee doe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire our ſelues from ſinne; and from the deſires and allurements of the world, and doe die to all carnall
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:12333:6"/>
delights; as that Apoſtle did, which ſaid, <hi>The world is crucified to mee, and I vnto the world:</hi> thus to die to ſinne, is to be deliuered from ſinne, and to liue with Chriſt.</p>
               <p>The third is,<note place="margin">3. A natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall dying; which is, the diſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution of the Soule from the body.</note> the looſing of the Soule fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the body: which is implyed by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> ſaying, <hi>I deſire to bee diſſolued:</hi> namely, by the diſ-iunction of the body from the Soule. This diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolution is a deliuerie out of the priſon of this life, with the ſtinke and filth wherof we are infected &amp; defiled: but by death the bands are looſed, and the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:12333:7"/>
priſon ſet open, where out wee flye freely vnto Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, where we are recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued pure and cleane wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhen, by the bloud of the immaculate Lambe: and beeing cloathed vvith his white garment of inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cency, wee are filled with delights, and with the fruition of the light inac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſible.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:12333:7"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 2.</hi> To learne to die well, ought to be the chiefe ſtudy and labour of our life.</head>
               <p>LIfe is a debt to Death: and Death a debt to Nature; or rather natures ſeruant: for if death vvere not, what complaints and murmurings would there be againſt Nature, if here, againſt our willes, wee ſhould ſtill liue, and not haue our liues freed by death? If death were quite taken from vs, no doubt, wee ſhould more deſire it, then now we feare it, and
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:12333:8"/>
thirſt more after it, then after life it ſelfe. Of all leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, and of all learnings, none is more weighty, none more diuine, then to learne to die well, which is, to die willingly, and to die in the faith, feare, and fauour of God.<note place="margin">In lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to dye well, conſiſteth our eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare.</note> To learne to die well, is the chiefeſt thing, and dutie of life; and a leſſon worthy our beſt and chiefeſt labours; for therein conſiſteth our eternall welfare. Therfore there is nothing, that ought ſo often, and ſo much to bee thought vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as Death: inſomuch, as if it were poſſible, the
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:12333:8"/>
the whole moments of our life ſhould bee no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe, but a learning or taking out of ſome new leſſon of death.</p>
               <p>What is it with the Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtorian, to know what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers haue done, and to neglect the true know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our ſelues? with the Lawyer, to learne the common Lawes of the Realme, and to forget the common Law of Nature, which is, that all muſt die? What is it, for the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Politicians, by their reaching wits, to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe great and high mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, and in the end, to die
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:12333:9"/>
like ſimple men?<note place="margin">True wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome is to be wiſe vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a mans own ſoule.</note> True wiſedome is to bee wiſe vnto a mans owne ſoule: and they onely are wiſe, and they only liue, which finde time and leaſure, wherein to learne to die well: for no part of our life is worthy the name of a life, but what is ſpent in the ſtudy of wiſedome: and the greateſt part of true wiſdome, is to learne to die well.</p>
               <p>The perfection of our knowledge, is to know God and our ſelues: our ſelues we beſt know, when we doe well conſider our mortall being: for man is
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:12333:9"/>
neuer ſo diuine, as when he conſidereth well of his mortall nature, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues hee was borne to die.</p>
               <p>As men wee die natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally; as Chriſtians we die religiouſly: By mortifying the old man, we endeuour to die to the world: By a vertuous diſpoſing of our ſelues for the day of our departure, wee learne to die in the world: By our dying to the world, Chriſt is ſaid, to come and liue in vs: By our dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in the world, wee are ſaid, to goe and liue with Chriſt. Seeing therefore
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:12333:10"/>
to die, is ſo neceſſary, and to die well, is ſo Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anly: let euery one apply himſelfe diligently to this learning, as the greateſt part of true wiſedome, which aymeth wholy at this end.</p>
               <p>In this life to ſequeſter ones ſelfe, <hi>Vac<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>re Deo,</hi> to be at leaſure for God, and to prepare for a peaceable paſſage out of this life, in ſuch ſort, that at that houre wee may haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing elſe to doe, but to die, and quietly and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentedly to depart this life, is a moſt excellent and happy thing: <hi>Nihil
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:12333:10"/>
ſuauius in hac vita, quàm vt quietus fiat exitus ex eadem.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Martha</hi> combred her ſelfe about many things, but <hi>Mary</hi> choſe the good part: let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore leane to <hi>Martha,</hi> to be <hi>ſollicita circa multa,</hi> and to beleeue with <hi>Mary, vnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt neceſſarium:</hi> which is, to learne to die well.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> Why men doe ſeldome enter into a ſerious remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance of their end.</head>
               <p>THE cauſe why men doe ſo ſeldome re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:12333:11"/>
their end, is, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are perſwaded by the old enemy of man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, that they ſhall not die, ſaying <hi>(Nequaquam moriemini:)</hi> &amp; therefore in his ſubtilty and cunning hee perſwades them, that the remembra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of death is but a melancholy con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit: leſt it ſhould make, in their hearts, too deepe an impreſſion of the feare of God; therefore to driue away all, he ſaith, <hi>Eritis vt dij:</hi> whereas the Prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> tels vs, <hi>Moriere. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitutum eſt omnibus ſemel mori;</hi> it is enacted, that <hi>All muſt die.</hi> And this, the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:12333:11"/>
daily inſtances of death doe continually confirme vnto vs: the conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on whereof may iuſtly moue vs, to ſhake off this ſtrange forgetfulneſſe of our end, vnleſſe wee will verifie that complaint of <hi>Cyprian: Nolumus agnoſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere, quod ignorare non poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumus:</hi> We will not know that, which we cannot but know. How often doe we heare the ſolemne knell, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ourſelues ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſay, wel, ſome body is dying? Doe we not paſſe by the graues of many, who, for age and ſtrength, might rather haue ſeen vs lead the way?
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:12333:12"/>
and yet for all this, we liue as if we had nothing to do with Death: but howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer, ſure we are, we ſhall one day finde, that Death will haue to doe with vs, when he ſhall ſtrip vs into a ſhrowding ſheete, binde vs hand and foote, and make our laſt bed, to bee the hard Graue.</p>
               <p>The daily inſtances of Death do euidently ſhew, what ſhall ſhortly after betide our ſelues: and they that are not moued with theſe ſad ſpectacles, are in a dangerous Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thargie of the ſoule. Of which ſort of men, that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:12333:12"/>
moane of <hi>Moſes</hi> may iuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be renued: <hi>O that this people were wiſe, and would remember the latter things:</hi> That they would call to minde, <hi>The dayes will come</hi> (and GOD knowes how ſoone) <hi>when the keepers of the houſe ſhall tremble,</hi> (which are the hands:) <hi>when the ſtrong men ſhall bow themſelues</hi> (to wit, the legges) <hi>when they ſhall waxe darke, that looke out of the windowe</hi> (that is, the eyes:) <hi>when the eares and daughters of Muſick ſhall be abaſed: when the Graſhop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pers or bended ſhoulders ſhall be a burthen: when the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:12333:13"/>
wheele ſhall be broken at the Ceſterne</hi> (that is the heart, whence the head draweth the powers of life:) in a word, when <hi>duſt ſhall turne to duſt againe;</hi> the ioynts ſtifned, the ſences benum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, the countenance pale, the blood cold, the eyes clozed, the browes hardned, the whole body all in a faint ſweat, wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried, nature being now ſpent.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>O earth, earth, earth,</hi> ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Ieremie</hi> 22.29. The firſt earth ſheweth whence we were: the ſecond, what we are: the third, what we ſhal be.
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:12333:13"/>
Whereupon the Wiſe man could not but won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, why any ſhould be puffed vp with pride, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering he was but earth, ſaying, <hi>Quid ſuperbis, terra?</hi> O earth, why art thou proud, ſince all thy pompe, and thy ſelfe, is no better then the ground thou treadeſt vpon? Our firſt Parents were at firſt clothed with the skinnes of dead beaſts, that they might remember the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon thereof, which was ſinne; and what ſhould likewiſe become of our ſelues. <hi>Let the rich and moſt glorious amongst men</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:12333:14"/>
(ſaith the Prophet) <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member themſelues to bee but men: that they ſhall carry nothing away with them: that all their pompe ſhall leaue them: and they follow the generation of their Fathers: yet for all this, they thinke they ſhall continue for euer, and that their houſes ſhall indure from generation to genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, calling their lands af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter their owne names:</hi> this is their fooliſhneſſe.</p>
               <p>One of the greateſt euils in the life of man, is a careleſſe neglect of Gods worſhip: and one of the greateſt cauſes of this neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:12333:14"/>
is the forgetfulneſſe of his end: therefore (ſaith <hi>Gregory</hi>) do ſo many caſt off all care of Chriſtian piety, becauſe they neuer remember their end: for, for the moſt part, wee are euen out of the world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we euer conſider our fraile condition in the ſame; and begin then to direct our courſe aright, when the time is come, ra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther to make an end: Whereas theſe are no dayes to liue ſecurely in but rather high time for euery one to amend one that God may haue mercy vpon all. To let all alone
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:12333:15"/>
vntill it bee too late, was their folly, who long ſince were drownd in the floud: to caſt onely for wealth and eaſe, was his worldly wiſedome, that made a ſodaine farewell fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> both, and was forced that very night to make his end, when he thought to begin to take his eaſe. Satan hath not a more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous deuice, whereby to draw men from God, then by ſtealing from their hearts a remembrance of their end: and there can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not bee a more effectuall meane, whereby to ſhake off the allurements of this
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:12333:15"/>
life (as <hi>Paul</hi> did the Viper into the fire) then by a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious meditation of our end.</p>
               <p>There is nothing more like to the graue, then our beds: to the winding ſheet, then the ſheetes of our beds: to the Worms, then the Fleas: to the ſound of the Archangels Trumpet, then the crow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Cocke, or mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning wakener. To medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate of our end at our ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing downe; and at riſing vp, to call to minde our ioyfull Reſurrection: to make this remembrance, the key to open the day,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:12333:16"/>
and to ſhut in the night, is an excellent and neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie practice. Let vs there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, euery houre of the day, remember that ſo much of our life is ſpent: euery euening remember death: euery night goe to bed, as wee would to our graues; lappe vs in our ſheetes, as in our winding ſheetes; and reſt attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing for that wakener, that ſhal ſummon vs to Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               <p>Thus is Death often to be thought vpon; not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for that it comes vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certainly; but becauſe it helpeth much to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:12333:16"/>
of this world: for hee eaſily contemnes the things of this life, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolues himſelfe continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly for death: and as Saint <hi>Ierome</hi> ſaith, <hi>Qui quotidiè recordatur ſe eſſe moritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum, contemnit praeſentia, &amp; ad futura feſtinat:</hi> hee that doth remember, that die he muſt, little regards things preſent, &amp; haſteth towards things to come. All which, the old enemy of mankinde perceiuing, how neceſſary it is, for man to remember his end, ſeekes by his pleaſant allurements of intiſing va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, to drawe him from
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:12333:17"/>
this frequent meditation of Death: whereas in deed, there is nothing, wherein ordinary medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is ſo neceſſary, as in the dayly meditating vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> The neceſsitie of our dayly meditating vpon Death.</head>
               <p>NAture it ſelf teaches, &amp; experience ſhewes it daily, that we muſt leaue the vanities and delights of this world, and they vs, with how great a luſt and pleaſure ſo euer we be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:12333:17"/>
after them: for death is the common and ineui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Law of Nature: it is the condition of all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kinde, and the way of all fleſh. In this way, <hi>Adam</hi> firſt entred and continued 930. yeeres, and yet dyed: ſo did <hi>Methuſalem,</hi> and continued 969. yeres, and yet dyed: ſo did the reſt of the Fathers of the firſt age, euery one ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred yeeres, and yet dyed: and ſo did the Fathers in all ages vnto this houre: neither haue they, nor can we, paſſe any other way vnto eternall happines: for Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe,
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:12333:18"/>
went not vp into glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, but by paſsing firſt through death: for there is no other paſſage to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mortality, then onely by Death. Therefore to learn to die, and to learne to die betimes, is an excellent, &amp; a neceſſarie thing; and a thing, that wee can but once put in practice: and it is the end that crownes the worke, &amp; a good death that honors a mans whole life: therefore with the greater reaſon, wee ought the more carefully to me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate thereon continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. both in regard of the incertainty of our depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:12333:18"/>
hence, which, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly may be, at the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant of our thought: as alſo, for that hee which foreſees his owne Death, dies more willingly,<note place="margin">Many tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend an vnexpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed death.</note> then he whom death ſurpriſeth of a ſudden (for many tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments attend an vnexpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted death:) therfore that our departure may be the more cheereful, when that ineuitable houre comes, it is neceſſarie, that wee ſhould meditate of it long before it doe come: for the more we do meditate of Death, the leſſe wee feare it, and the leſſe wee feare it, the greater is our faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:12333:19"/>Heere wee haue no cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine heritage, but are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly tenants at will, in a poore clay cottage, the foundation and ſtrength of which building, is but a few bones tyed together, with ſtrings or ſinewes: &amp; the chiefe pillar, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon the whole frame ſtayes, is only the drawing of a little breath, which being once ſtopt, cauſeth the whole building to fall <hi>in manus Domini:</hi> therefore we ought euer to be ready to flit, whenſoeuer death commandeth, ſince flit we muſt: and the laſt day of life, is vnknowne vnto vs,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:12333:19"/>
to the end wee may euery day bee prepared for Death: Let vs then ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect this definitiue houre without feare: ſo ſhall the day which we feare to be our laſt, be our natiui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie vnto an eternall life. That then which neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily muſt befall vs, it is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie, that wee ſhould continually thinke of; ſo ſhall wee accompliſh our life, before our death. This mooued <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of <hi>Arima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thea,</hi> to prepare a ſepul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chre for himſelfe in a gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, at the which, hee might dayly meditate vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Death. This mooued
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:12333:20"/>
the Noble men of <hi>Aethio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pia,</hi> to keep their cuſtome, that whenſoeuer they went forth to the field to recreate themſelues, they cauſed to bee carried be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them, a golden baſon full of earth, together with the ſigne of the Croſſe, to remember them, that they were but earth, and to earth they ſhould returne: and that only in the death of Chriſt crucified, they had co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort againſt death, and aſſured hope of life. This moued <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedon</hi> to command his Page, euery morning, to cry thrice in his eare, <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member,</hi>
                  <pb n="31" facs="tcp:12333:20"/>
Philip, <hi>thou art but a mortall man.</hi> This moued alſo the ancient <hi>Aegyp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians</hi> at all their banquets, to haue placed in the ſight of the banquetters, the image &amp; picture of death, to make them in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt of their pleaſures, to remember the end; and ſo to moderate the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues from falling into ſuch vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as eaſily ariſe of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperancy. And finally, this moued the godly Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Ierome,</hi> vvhether hee did eate or drink, or what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer elſe he did, ſtrongly to imagine the ſounding of the Trumpet, ſummo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:12333:21"/>
him to Iudgement: therfore this warning that the Wiſe-man giues to the youth, that think their luſty age will neuer bee ſpent, and therefore giue themſelues to all licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſenſualitie, ought to be well remembred of all: <hi>For all theſe things</hi> (ſaith the Preacher) <hi>GOD will bring thee to Iudgement:</hi> therefore, <hi>Remember thy Creator in the dayes of thy youth, before the dayes come, wherein thou ſhalt ſay, I haue no pleaſure in them.</hi> One generation co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth, &amp; another goeth, but the earth ſtandeth ſtill; euen
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:12333:21"/>
as a Stage, whereon euery one hath his part to play for a time, and then to put off his Maske; and leauing the vanities of this life, to retire himſelfe to his duſt. It ſtands with life, as with a Stage-play, it is no mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter how long it laſts, but how wel it is acted: where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer thou endeſt, it is all one: end where thou wilt, ſo thou concludeſt with a good period.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:12333:22"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 5.</hi> Neceſsary obſeruations in our meditation of Death.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IN our meditation of Death, we ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, that the wages of ſinne, is death; to the end it ſhould ſtrike to our hart, with a terrour of ſinne, to make vs the more earneſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to repent our ſins, and to redeeme the time, that God ſpares vs with a rich amendment of our life: &amp; to thirſt after the remedy, which is, the mercy of God offred vnto vs, in the merits and Death of our
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:12333:22"/>
Lord and Sauiour Ieſus Chriſt, that we may make a happy change, from mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſery temporall, to euerlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing felicity.</p>
               <p n="2">2 Secondly, that this vile, brickle, weake eſtate of our life is to be weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: to make vs eſchew pride, ambition, lecherie, drunkenneſſe, gluttony, delicate feeding, pampe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, decking of this filthy clay, and ſuch other vices of the fleſh.</p>
               <p n="3">3 Thirdly, in that wee brought nothing with vs into this world, ſo muſt we carry away nothing with vs at our death; whereby
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:12333:23"/>
we are to learne, to eſchew auarice, coueting of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers lands and goods, V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſury, Oppreſſion, and all other vnlawfull meanes, commonly vſed, for attai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to riches and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour in this world: and as the Apoſtle counſels, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing meat and raiment be content, &amp; ſo to vſe things temporall, as by them wee may come to things eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. For wee came not into this world, to build houſes, or to purchaſe lands, to ioyne houſe to houſe, but rather by this our ſhort continuance, we are put in minde, to haue
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:12333:23"/>
                  <hi>temporalia in vſu, aeterna in deſiderio:</hi> and to vſe this world, as if we vſed it not,<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.31.</note> and ſo be gone.</p>
               <p n="4">4 Laſtly, inſomuch as death indifferently and without reſpect, knocks as well at the gates of prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Palaces, as at the dores of poore Cottages: and takes pleaſure to vvound, as vvell the flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing youth, as the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed Age: ſhooting his darts continually, by Land, by Sea, by day, by night, at home, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad (and neuer miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing:) let all eſtates at all times, and in all places, be
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:12333:24"/>
alwayes ready armed, againſt the aſſaults of Death.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 6.</hi> Againſt the feare of Death.</head>
               <p>DEath is the ineuitable Law of nature: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to feare that which cannot bee auoyded, is meere folly. But our feare of death proceedes from doubt: and doubt from vnbeliefe; and our vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe chiefly from igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; becauſe wee know not the good that is elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where;
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:12333:24"/>
and doe not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that our part is in it: ſo that, true knowledge, and true faith, driues away all feare of death. Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of heauenly things, makes vs willing to part with earthly. Hee cannot contemne this life, that knowes not the other: and he is not worthy to liue in the other, that is vnwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling to die in this: to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe this life, is to thinke of heauen: and not to feare Death, is to thinke of that glorious life that followes it. If we can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure pain for health, much more ought wee (at our
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:12333:25"/>
laſt) to abide a few pangs (that cannot laſt) for an euerlaſting glory.</p>
               <p>How fondly doe wee feare a vanquiſht enemie, ouer whom Chriſt hath already triumphed: by whoſe death, death is ſwallowed vp in victory, and we thereby deliuered from the tyranny thereof? It is enough to vs, that Chriſt died for vs, who had not died neither, but that wee might die the more willingly, and with greater ſafety.</p>
               <p>Death is neceſſarily an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexed to nature; and life is giuen vs, with a condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:12333:25"/>
to die; and our Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, in his mercy conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nues the vſe of our life, to this end onely, that we may learne rightly to die. There is but one com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon rode to all fleſh: and there are no by-paths of any fayrer or neerer way; no not for Princes. Haue we bin at ſo many graues, and ſo oft ſeene our ſelues die in our friends; and doe wee ſhrinke when our courſe commeth? Imagine thou wert ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empt from the common Law of mankinde; yet aſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſure thy ſelfe, death is not now ſo fearefull, as thy
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:12333:26"/>
life would then be weari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome.</p>
               <p>Thinke not ſo much what Death is, as from whom he comes, and for what. Wee receiue euen homely Meſſengers from great perſons, not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reſpect to their Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters: and what matters it who he be, ſo he bring vs good newes? and what better newes can there be then this, That God ſends for thee, to take poſſeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a Kingdome. Let them then feare Death, that knowes not Death, to bee the meſſenger of Gods iuſtice and mercy.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="43" facs="tcp:12333:26"/>To die is a thing natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, neceſſary, and reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable. Naturall,<note place="margin">Naturall.</note> for it is the generall Law of the whole world, <hi>that all muſt die:</hi> and our very eſſence is equally parted into life and death: for the firſt day of our birth, ſets vs as well in the way to death as to life.</p>
               <p>Death is the condition of our creation: and life is giuen vs with an excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of death: to die ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, is as naturall as to be borne: and as fooliſh is hee that feareth to die, as to be old. To be vnwilling to die, is to be vnwilling
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:12333:27"/>
to be a man: for all men are mortall.</p>
               <p>Death being then a thing ſo naturall, why ſhould it be feared? The feare of griefe and paine is naturall, but not of death. Children and mad men feare not death: why ſhould not reaſon then be as able to furniſh vs with ſecurity, as they are forti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by their ſimplicity &amp; idiotiſme? Beaſts feare not death: therefore it is not nature that teacheth vs to feare death, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to attend and receiue it, as ſent by her whoſe ſeruant it is. Fooles feare
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:12333:27"/>
death, and wiſe men at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend it. It is folly to grieue at that, which cannot be amended: therfore when <hi>Dauid</hi> vnderſtood of the death of his child, he cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to ſorrow any longer for him, ſaying: While he liued, there was hope: but being dead, there was no remedy, and ſo his care ended.</p>
               <p>Death is a debt of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, which muſt be payd whenſoeuer it is deman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. It is no taking day with God, when his will is to call for it. Therefore it is in vaine to flie from that, which wee cannot
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:12333:28"/>
ſhunne: and thoſe things which of neceſsity muſt be performed of vs, ought to be done cheerefully, &amp; not by compulſion: as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> ſaith, Let vs make that voluntarie, which is neceſſarie, and yeeld it to God as a gift, which we ſtand bound to pay, as a due debt.</p>
               <p>Death is a happines to the faithfull, becauſe it is a deliuerance both of ſoule and body, from all miſery and ſinne. By death the world was redeemed: to ſuch therefore as doe be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue in Chriſt their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer, death is to them
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:12333:28"/>
an aduantage, and a thing rather to be deſired then feared: for they onely are affrighted and daunted with the feare of death, that are deſtitute of <hi>faith</hi> and <hi>hope.</hi> If thou belee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt in God, why art thou not forward to goe to Chriſt, who died for thee? There cannot be a more happy thing, then deuout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to render thy life into his hands, who to ſpare thee, ſpared not himſelfe, but gaue his life for thee. <hi>Chriſt</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul) is gaine to me, both in life and death:</hi> holding it for a wonderfull gaine, to be
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:12333:29"/>
no more ſubiect to ſinne. It is a more grieuous thing to liue in ſinne, then to die: for as long as a wicked man liues, his ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity increaſeth: if he die, his ſinne ceaſeth: the euill therefore of death, is only in ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie.</note>Death brings an equall, and an ineuitable neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie ouer all: therfore did nature make that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon to all, which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly was feared of all: to the end, that ſuch an equality might aſſwage the rigour and ſeuerity of death, and that none might iuſtly complaine of
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:12333:29"/>
death, from which, none was euer exempted.<note place="margin">1 Two cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes that lets men from dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly. Lacke of faith.</note> But one chiefe cauſe that lets vs from dying willingly, is lacke of <hi>faith:</hi> for had we <hi>faith,</hi> we would night and day deſire this meſſenger of the Lords Iuſtice and Mercy, to deliuer vs out of this miſerable life, that wee might enter into the fruition of eternall felici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: for hauing confidence in GOD, wee ſhall finde death to be as a guide, to bring vs to our euerlaſting home.<note place="margin">2 Loue of the world.</note> Another cauſe of the feare of death, is the loue of the world: for they feare death moſt, that
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:12333:30"/>
moſt loues the world, and giues themſelues moſt to the pleaſures and delights of this life, which they feare to be depriued of by death. To feare death, is for a man to be enemie to himſelfe, and to his owne life: for he can neuer liue at eaſe and contentedly, that feareth to die: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to contemne death, is a thing one ſhould learne betimes: for without this meditation, none ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> haue any repoſe in minde, ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it is moſt certaine, that die we muſt, not knowing when; and it may be, at the very inſtant of our
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:12333:30"/>
thought; how then can any enioy a peaceable ſoule, who feares death,<note place="margin">Improui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence ads terror vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to death.</note> which threatens him eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry minute of this life? There is not a more dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous enemie againſt a mans ſelfe, then himſelfe, by his follies, his fanta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies, his vanities, his ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fetting and exceſſe; his luſt, his anger, his feares, and the reſt of his affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; whereof within his breaſt he foſters a Forreſt full. That man is onely a free man, which feares not death; and contrarily, life is but a ſlauerie, if it were not made free by
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:12333:31"/>
death: for death is the onely ſtay of our libertie, and the common and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die remedy againſt all e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uils, and the onely meane to all good. It is then a miſery, (and miſerable are all that doe it) to trouble their liues with the feare of death: and their death, with the deſire of life.</p>
               <p>For a man to torment himſelfe with the feare of death is great weakeneſſe and cowardlineſſe: for there is no paſsion in the minde of man ſo weake, but can maſter the feare of Death: and therefore death is no ſuch enemie,
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:12333:31"/>
when a man hath ſo many followers about him, that can conquer him: reuenge triumphs ouer death: loue eſteemes it not: honour aſpireth to it: deliuery fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ignominie chuſeth it: griefe flyeth to it: feare preoccupyeth it: what an extreme madnes is it then, for a man to torment him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe for nothing, and that willingly? <hi>Scienter fruſtrà niti, extremae dementiae eſt.</hi> Death beeing then ſo ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarie and ineuitable; it is to no purpoſe to feare it; for ſuch things as are certain as Death, we muſt attend; and in things paſt
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:12333:32"/>
remedy, we muſt be reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute: therefore making of neceſſity a vertue, we muſt welcome it, and receiue it kindely (for where there is not vertue and willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to death, life is but a ſeruitude:) and to bee truely free from the feare of death, is to thinke con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually on death: ſo ſhall wee thereby bee the more couragious againſt the neceſsitie of our depar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and iuſt.</note>To dye is a thing reaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable and iuſt: for it is but reaſon, that we giue place to others, ſince others haue giuen place to vs: and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:12333:32"/>
ſince we haue enioyed the places, offices, and herita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of them that were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs: it is but equall, that thoſe that doe come after vs, ſhould likewiſe poſſeſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> accordingly.</p>
               <p>It is a thing generall and common to al, to die: Why ſhould then any feare to goe, whither all the world goeth: where ſo many millions haue gone before, and ſo many milli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are to follow after? They whom wee ſuppoſe to be dead, do not periſh, but precede; they are on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſent before, whom we muſt preſently follow af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter:<pb n="56" facs="tcp:12333:33"/>
in which meane time, notwithſtanding, there is no long time betweene their meeting, and ours: for euery moment of this life, is the death of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: the time paſt is loſt and gone, death is already poſſeſſed thereof: onely the time preſent, we haue ſhare with death: ſo that euery day, we die by little and little: why then ſhould any feare that once, which is acted euery day? The death which wee ſo much feare and flye, takes not from vs life, but only giues it a truce, and intermiſſion for a little time: and as
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:12333:33"/>
for our bodies, they haue no more damage by death, then hath the ſeed, for hauing a little earth harrowed ouer it. Let eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry one therefore indeuour to make euery day, as it were, his laſt day: for to ſpurne againſt death, is to ſtriue againſt nature, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt our faith, &amp; againſt all dutie. Yet euery one hurries on his life, and tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels in the deſire of future things, and wearineſſe of preſent times; but hee which beſtowes his whole time, to learne how to die well, neither deſires, nor feares, what may happen
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:12333:34"/>
the day after: for vvhat can hee iuſtly feare, that hopes to die? according to that anſwere of the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedemonians</hi> vnto <hi>Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pater,</hi> who threatned them cruelly, if they yeelded not to his demand: It is not (ſaid they) in thy power, <hi>O Antipater,</hi> to threaten vs with any thing, that is worſe then death, &amp; death is welcome to vs.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:12333:34"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 7.</hi> How to carry our ſelues con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning Death.</head>
               <p>TO feare and flye death as an euill, is a thing not approoued by men of vnderſtanding, though by the greater partie it be practiſed: to deſire death, argues we are out of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie with the world: to contemne life, is vnthank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to nature; to at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend death, is good: but to flie and feare death, is againſt nature, reaſon, iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, and all dutie. If wee conſider death, as in it
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:12333:35"/>
ſelfe, then naturally wee feare it: but if we conſider it, as a meane to bring vs to Chriſt, then ought wee to imbrace it. The feare of death, in contemplati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the cauſe of it, and the iſſue of it, is religious: but the feare of it for it ſelfe, is a teſtimonie of great weakeneſſe. Men feare death, as children feare to goe in the darke: and as that naturall feare in children, is increaſed with tales, ſo is the other. There is not a thing, that men feare more then death: and there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, that hath leſſe occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:12333:35"/>
or matter of feare, then death: or that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarily, yeeldeth greater reaſons to perſwade vs with reſolution to accept of it: for if it bee an euill, it is of all euils the leaſt <hi>euill,</hi> and the euill that doth leaſt harme: nay, it is ſo farre from beeing an euill, that it is the onely remedie againſt all euils: for in this life, euils and dangers attend vs conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually: whereas by death, our life is exempted from all euils, and filled vvith eternall ioyes. Moreouer, if it bee an enemy, it is of all enemies the leaſt, or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:12333:36"/>
of all friends the beſt: for he brings vs out of all danger of enemies, into the protection and ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of our beſt and moſt aſſured friend for euer, Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt our onely Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and Redeemer. Wee muſt then thinke, that it is a meere opinion, and a vulgar errour, that hath wonne the world to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit ſo hardly of death. It is not death it ſelfe, that men are afraid of, but the opinion and apprehenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of death, that onely terrifies: now this terrible apprehenſion is grounded vpon a precedent opinion
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:12333:36"/>
of our infirmitie, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie to truth; for veritie incourageth, opinion dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs. Opinion bands it ſelfe againſt reaſon, and ſeekes to deface her, with the maske of death: it may bee, the ſpectacle of death diſpleaſeth, becauſe they that die, looke gaſtly: but this is not death, but the maske of death: that which is hid vnder it, is beautifull; for, death hath nothing in it that is feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full. Death then, in it ſelfe is not euill, therefore not to be feared.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:12333:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 8.</hi> This life is but a priſon, a pilgrimage, a warfare, and as a voyage vpon a tempeſtuous Sea.</head>
               <p>DEath is the ſoueraign good of Nature: and the onely pillar of our li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie: whereas this life is but a priſon, a pilgrimage, a warfare, &amp; as a voyage vpon a tempeſtuous Sea.</p>
               <p>In this life wee are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes in priſon, and our Soule incloſed in the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, as in a priſon, which de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires releaſement, as the thirſty doe coole &amp; freſh waters.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:12333:37"/>Our life is but a <hi>Iacobs</hi> pilgrimage,<note place="margin">Pilgri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage.</note> the dayes whereof are in number few, and in condition euil: as <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaid, The dayes of my peregrination <hi>are few and euill:</hi> and as they are few and euill: ſo is the time of our change moſt vncertaine: of which cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie, we are put in mind in the Lords Prayer, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Giue vs this day, &amp;c.</hi> wee ſay, <hi>this day,</hi> as vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine of to morrow. Saint <hi>Peters</hi> argument to draw the Iewes from car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall deſires, was, <hi>Obſecro vos tanquam aduenas &amp; peregrinos;</hi> I beſeech you
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:12333:38"/>
brethren, as Pilgrims and ſtrangers; as if he ſhould haue ſaid, Seeing you are in this world, but as way<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faring men, ſtay not your ſelues vpon carnall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires (the baits of Satan, &amp; the bane of your ſoules) but abſtaine from them. The holy Ghoſt doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemble the ſtate of man, to graſſe, to a ſhaddow, to ſmoake, to a vapour, to a flower, things of no con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance, thereby to inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate vnto vs, a conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of our vnconſtant and variable eſtate. Let vs therefore in this life, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditate of nothing more,
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:12333:38"/>
then of our pilgrimage: for here wee ſhall not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes be; and let vs by liuing well, prepare vs there a place from whence wee ſhall neuer depart: and ſince Chriſt hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared Heauen for vs; let vs prepare our ſelues for Heauen.</p>
               <p>The life of man is a warfare:<note place="margin">Warfare.</note> therefore vvee ought to be euer looking for our change, for men in warre hourely expect their change, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaid, <hi>All the dayes of this my warfare doe I wait, till my change doe come:</hi> whoſe courſe if wee would fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low,
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:12333:39"/>
then ſhould wee bee out of the danger of time, to wiſh to liue one houre longer: for then ſhould wee bee ſo armed againſt the aſſaults of death, as that, nothing could hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen, that ſhould light vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs ſodainly, or vnloo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked for! therefore well did one counſel, ſaying, <hi>Think to liue but for an houre, and account euery day a new life:</hi> for he who euery day puts an end to his life, hath no need of time: and liue thoſe few dayes that remain, to the Lord, whom thou oughteſt to haue ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued all daies of thy life.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="69" facs="tcp:12333:39"/>To the wayfaring man, it is no little comfort, to talke of his iourneys end: ioyfully doth the bond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man reckon of the yeere of <hi>Iubile:</hi> this weariſome pilgrimage, this burthen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome bondage of ours, may iuſtly moue vs, often to remember our end: for as Saint <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Quid eſt diu viuere, niſi diu tor queri?</hi> what is it to liue long, but to bee long tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented?</p>
               <p>Death is like to ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling on the Sea:<note place="margin">Death is like a voy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>age vpon a tempe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtuous Sea</note> for whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wee ſleepe, or wake, ſtill wee are making to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the hauen: ſo whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:12333:40"/>
we direct our courſe towards death or no, ſure we are, wee cannot poſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly alter our courſe from death. This life cannot bee more fitly compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to any thing, then to a Ship in the midſt of a tempeſtuous Sea: for, there it is in danger of tempeſts; heere of quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands: on this ſide of Py<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rats: on the other, of Rockes: ſo in this life; here is the Diuell; there the world: on this ſide the fleſh, on that ſide, ſinne, which neuer forſakes vs, ſo long as life laſts. So that in this vaſt Sea, ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:12333:40"/>
to all ſtorms and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſts, we that ſayle there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, are euer in feare &amp; dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and are neuer glad, but when wee approch to the Hauen: euen ſo ſhould we be, when we draw nye vnto death; which is, the Port, which brings vs to eternall ſecuritie. If ſome bitternes were not ming<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with death, doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe men would runne vnto it, with great deſire and indiſcretion. To keepe therefore a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, that is, that men neither loue life, nor feare death too much, ſweetneſſe and ſharpneſſe,
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:12333:41"/>
are therein tempered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 9.</hi> The vulgar remedy against Death.</head>
               <p>THe remedy that the vulgar ſort doe giue herein, is too ſimple, and that is, neuer to thinke or ſpeake of death: but ſuch a kinde of careleſneſſe can not lodge in the head of a man of vnderſtanding; for at the laſt it would coſt him too deare:<note place="margin">Many tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend an vnexpect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed death.</note> for death comming vnawares and vnexpected, what tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, out-cryes, furies
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:12333:41"/>
and deſpaires are there commonly ſeene? wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome aduiſeth much bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that is, to attend and expect death with a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant foot, and to incoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter it: and the better to do this, it giues vs contrarie counſel to the vulgar ſort, that is, to haue it alwayes in our thoughts (ſo ſhall we neuer feare it:) to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtome our ſelues vnto it, and to be familiar with it (for familiaritie cannot ſtand with feare:) to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it vnto vs at al houres, and to expect it: not only in places ſuſpected and dangerous, but in the
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:12333:42"/>
middeſt of feaſts &amp; ſports; following herein the cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of the <hi>Aegyptians,</hi> who in their ſolemn ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quets, placed the image of death before their eyes: and of the Chriſtians, who haue their Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yards neere their Temples and other publike and fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quented places, that men might alwayes bee put in minde of Death: and that others are dead, that thought to haue liued as long as our ſelues: and that, that which happened then to them, may happen now to vs. It is vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine in what place death
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:12333:42"/>
attends vs, &amp; therefore let vs attend death in all pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and be alwayes ready to receiue it.</p>
               <q>
                  <l>Omnem crede diem,</l>
                  <l>tibi diluxiſſe ſupremum,</l>
                  <l>Grata ſuperueniet,</l>
                  <l>quae non ſperabitur hora.</l>
               </q>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 10.</hi> Grieuances and excuſes of fearfull men to couer and colour their complaints of Death.</head>
               <p n="1">1. IT grieues them to die yong, and they com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaine that death preuents them, and cuts them off,
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:12333:43"/>
in the flower and ſtrength of their yeeres: this is the complaint of the vulgar ſort, who meaſure all by the ell: as though whom God loued beſt, hee did not ſooneſt take fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> hence. <hi>Enoch</hi> walked according to God, and was no more ſeene: for God tooke him vp; ſo that to pleaſe God, is to be taken quickly from the corruptions of the world: So did he by <hi>Ioſias,</hi> his ſoule pleaſed the Lord; therefore he made haſte, to take him out of the midſt of iniquity.</p>
               <p>As Parents containe their children within their
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:12333:43"/>
duties, by a ſeuere &amp; ſharp diſcipline: ſo God vvill not ſuffer thoſe hee loues, to haue the head; but proues them, tryes them, and prepares them for his ſeruice; laying the bridle on thoſe he loues not: for thoſe he doth but weaken and effeminate for euils to come. Great vertue and long life, doe ſeldome or neuer meete together: a a little man is as perfect a man, as a greater: and nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther men, nor their liues, are meaſured by the ell.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> They are troubled, to thinke they muſt leaue their Parents, and their
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:12333:44"/>
friends: as though, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they goe, they ſhall not finde more: and thoſe, they leaue behinde them, ſhould not ſhortly follow after them.</p>
               <p>But what ſhall become of their ſmall Children and Orphanes, left with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out guide, without ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port? as if thoſe their chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, were more theirs then Gods: or as if they could loue them more, then hee that is their firſt, and trueſt Father: and how many ſuch, ſo left, haue riſen to higher place, and greater ability then other men? Why
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:12333:44"/>
are they offended vvith death, ſince it quits them of all griefe? To returne from whence thou ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſt, what burden, vvhat griefe is it?</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> But it takes vs, from that wee know, and haue been accuſtomed vnto, and brings vs vnto an eſtate vnknowne; it takes vs fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the light, to bring vs to darknes: and to conclude, it is our end, our ruine, our diſſolution.</p>
               <p>Theſe are their weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt obiections: where unto we may anſwere in a word: That death beeing the ineuitable Law of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:12333:45"/>
it is a folly, to feare that, which a man can not auoid: and to feare death, is a meere folly, becauſe things certaine, are ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pected; doubtfull things onely feared: Theſe peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple make not their count well: for in ſtead of taking any thing from vs, it giues vs all: in ſtead of bringing vs into darknes, it taketh it from vs, and puts vs into the light.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:12333:45"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 10.</hi> How we may deſire Death.</head>
               <p>TO deſire death, as the retrait and onely ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, from the torments of this life: as the ſoueraigne good of nature, and as the onely ſtay &amp; pillar of our liberty; is beſitting a good and a ſetled ſoule. It is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>becillity to yeeld vnto e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill: but it is folly, to nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh it. It is a good time to die, when to liue, is rather a burthen, then a bleſſing. There is more ill in life, then good: and to increaſe our torment, is againſt na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:12333:46"/>
Wilfully to hinder our owne health, is, not onely againſt the courſe of nature, but alſo a temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the God of nature. To wiſh to die ſooner, or to liue longer, then it ſhall ſeeme good vnto the Gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer of life, is a great in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gratitude. A liuely appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion and deſire of the life to come, makes a man to thirſt after death, as af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a great gaine: as after the ſeed of a better life: as the bridge vnto Paradiſe: as the way to all good; and as an earneſt penny of the Reſurrection. A firme beliefe and hope of
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:12333:46"/>
theſe things, is incompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tible, with the feare and horrour of death: it per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwades rather to be wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of this life, and to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire death, <hi>Vitam habere in patientia, &amp; morte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derio.</hi> Therefore haue Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſophers and others bin iuſtly reproched, that play the publike diſſemblers, and doe not in verity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue that, which they doe ſo much talke of, and ſo highly commend, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that happy immorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie, and thoſe vnſpeake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able pleaſures in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond life: ſince they doubt and feare death ſo much
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:12333:47"/>
the neceſſary paſſage vnto immortality.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 12.</hi> The miſerable ſtate and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of this preſent life.</head>
               <p>BEhold the miſerable eſtate of this brickle body, ſubiect to all iniu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of fortune, that is, of ſuch miſeries and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiefes, as GOD by his prouidence ſendes, and ſowes thorow the world for ſinne. Then conſider whereabout this life is oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupied, how vainely, how dangerouſly, how paine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, how grieuouſly: and
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:12333:47"/>
in what feare, care, griefe, ſadnes, ſorrow, and vexa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it liues in: together with the infinite diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tents and diſcomforts of the minde. Now the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reſt and reliefe from all this, is in, and by death, whereby we ſhall change theſe pains into pleaſures, theſe dangers into ſafety, this wicked and euill com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany, with that moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py ſociety of the bleſſed and glorious Trinitie. If wee run thorow the ages and occupations of this life, it wil be thought wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thier the name of death, then life.</p>
               <q>
                  <pb n="86" facs="tcp:12333:48"/>
                  <l>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ita mihi haec mors eſt,</l>
                  <l>mors haec mihi vita perennis:</l>
                  <l>In vita exilium,</l>
                  <l>patria eſt in morte propinqua.</l>
               </q>
               <p>Thus is the perfect age of man conſumed, in va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, vexation, mourning, and miſchiefe, till heauie and burthenſome age ouertake him, wherein he can haue pleaſure of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing; wherein the poore conſcience is bitten, and pined with remembrance and remorſe of by-paſt ſinnes, the carkaſſe it ſelfe fraught with ſurfets; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch as there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing now, but oaſting in
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:12333:48"/>
the bowels, aking in the bones, gowt, grauel, ſtone and infinite other mala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies tormenting him, till hee haue brought his mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable life to end. <hi>Salo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi> ſought out carefully whatſoeuer ſeemed profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table or pleaſant, or might any wayes bring comfort or contentment, to the minde of man in this life: ſo that none could be able to match him ſince, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of his meanes and wiſedome; and yet hee found nothing but vanity and vexation of ſpirit. What vanity &amp; vexation is in euery eſtate of life,
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:12333:49"/>
by this one thing is moſt euident, that none is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent with his owne eſtate: but euery one eſteemes his neighbours better, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he knowes it not ſo well as his owne; and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferres the bitternes of his, with the pleaſures of his neighbours: ſo that the onely ignorance of the things of this world, makes the eſtimation of them: and when they are prooued by experience what they are, they are found to be nothing leſſe, then what they were ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed to be: ſo that, how much the more me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> luſted
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:12333:49"/>
after them, ſo much ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner doe they loath them, and muſt confeſſe in the end, all to be but vanity, labour and griefe.</p>
               <p>To the ſhortnes of life, may be added the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of the ſame, for all is not life, we here liue. The yeeres of mans life are few, but the miſeries ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of are infinite: therefore by the Grecians, the firſt day of the life of man, is called a beginning of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts. And S. <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith, of mans firſt en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trance into the world, <hi>Nondum loquitur, et tamen Prophetat;</hi> an Infant not
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:12333:50"/>
able to ſpeake, doth yet by teares prophecie of the ſorrowes incident to the life of man: ſo that the old ſaying may well be verified: <hi>Humana vita, non eſt vita, ſed calamitas,</hi> The life of man is rather calamity then life. All the dayes of this life, muſt we eate our bread in labour and ſorrow, vntill wee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to the earth, out of which we were taken: ſo that the dayes of man, by reaſon of ſinne, are no other but the dayes of ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row: for euery day hath <hi>ſuam malitiam,</hi> and euery night <hi>ſuum terrorem.</hi> Thus
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:12333:50"/>
is the eſtate and condition of life found troubleſome, euen of him to whom <hi>Abraham</hi> ſaid, <hi>Tu in vita,</hi> thou in thy life receiuedſt thy ioy: for the voluptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, in ſeeking his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, the ambitious his glory, the couetous his gaine, indure in this world a very ſeruitude and thral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of life: wherefore, for the tranſitory delights of this ſinfull world, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie are they that doe but ſee them, more happy that ſhunne them, &amp; moſt happy that are quite taken from them; whereby they are deliuered from this
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:12333:51"/>
irkeſome neceſſity of ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, and ſo ſhall grieue the holy Spirit no more.</p>
               <p>They only are wiſe, and they only liue, which finde time and leaſure, wherein to learne to die well: for without this knowledge, there is no more pleaſure in life, then in the fruition of that thing, which a man feareth alwayes to loſe. He hath ſpent his life wel, that hath learned to die well: and he hath loſt his whole time, that knowes not well how to end it. He ſhootes not well, that lookes not on the marke: and hee cannot liue well,
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:12333:51"/>
that hath not an eye to his death.</p>
               <p>The happineſſe of this life, conſiſts not in the length of time, but in the well vſing of time: for the vnprofitable part of mans life, is death. Our life is not to be meaſured accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the time, but ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to our actions: it imports not how long we liue, but how well. <hi>Non quàm diu, ſed quàm benè:</hi> Life is long enough, if we can but tell how to vſe it. In the longeſt life of all, the time which wee doe truly liue, is the leaſt of all: conſidering how much of
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:12333:52"/>
our life is ſpent in griefe, how much in cares, how much in ſickneſſe, how much in feares, how much in our young and vnpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable yeeres; and briefly, how much in ſleepe, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in in a manner we ſpend a moity of our liues. We re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued not a little ſhort life, but haue made it ſo our ſelues: euen as great wealth, when it comes into the hands of an vnthrift, is waſted in a moment: and meane ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches on the contrary, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe by the good im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment of one that is thrifty: euen ſo, this our
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:12333:52"/>
age is wonderfully exten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by him, that can diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe well of it.</p>
               <p>The ſwiftneſſe of time is incomprehenſible; and ſo it appeares principally, to thoſe that looke back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to it: and conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſwift and violent courſe of time, it is moſt ſtrange, that the greateſt part thereof ſhould bee imployed ſo much, in ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfluous things of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure or delight. So ſwift is the flight of time, as that the time we liue, is, but as it were a minute, and leſſe then a minute if it were poſsible: and yet not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding,
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:12333:53"/>
as little as it is, Nature hath diſtribu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted &amp; diuided it into ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny degrees: whereof part, ſhe hath allotted vnto In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fancie, part to Adoleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cencie, part to middle age, and part to old age (the next neighbour age to death.) Infancie is ſcarcely perceiued, youth is quickly ouer-blowne; middle age ſtayes not, &amp; old age is not long. Of all ages of our life, onely old age is not limited: but all the exerciſes of precedent times, and the delights and pleaſures of youth, do end and vaniſh in old age:
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:12333:53"/>
why then ſhould any thirſt after this life, which in effect is no better then a labourers worke, ſpent in toyle and trauell, conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming it ſelfe in vanities, ebbing away in words, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing a manſion place in duſt, and a life in ſlime and clay, without reſolution or conſtancy? What plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure then can there be in this life, when the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures thereof are nothing but vanities: and all the felicity thereof only <hi>ſplen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dida miſeria,</hi> a ſhining mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerie; nay, which is worſe, affliction of ſpirit? for where the loue of this
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:12333:54"/>
world enters, there is no longer reſt or quiet of minde; but warre of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, vexatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of thoughts, feares, cares, and vnquiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of ſoule, which in deede, is a moſt miſerable and pittifull affliction of ſpirit. All the commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of this world, are mixed with diſcommodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties (leſt wee ſhould loue them too much) and all the delights thereof are counterpoized with diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contentments: the grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous counterpoize wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, makes the miſeries of this world moſt intolera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: which made <hi>Iob</hi> to
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:12333:54"/>
deteſt the very day of his birth, ſaying; <hi>Let the day wherein I was borne, periſh:</hi> and made <hi>Salomon</hi> to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mend the condition of the dead, before the li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing: and to hold him better then them both, that neuer was borne, by reaſon he neuer walked in the vanities of this life, nor euer ſaw the wicked workes, that are commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vnder the Sunne. O miſerable and moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull world, whoſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeries are voyd of all con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, and whoſe hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pineſſe is mingled with all kinde of miſery! It de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiues
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:12333:55"/>
them that truſt it, afflicts them that ſerue it, damnes them that follow it: and ſooneſt of all, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gets them, that labour moſt of all for it. It is a very <hi>Iudas:</hi> for whom it kiſſeth, it betrayeth vnto Satan.</p>
               <p>The delights of ſinne goe downe pleaſantly, as wine doth at firſt; but at laſt, they bite like a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent: <hi>Oblectant ſenſum, ſed interficiunt ſpiritum:</hi> they delight the ſence, but ſlay the ſoule.</p>
               <p>If we be not moued to leaue this life, in reſpect of the miſeries (whereof it is
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:12333:55"/>
full:) yet ought wee to be willing to forgoe it, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of the infinite happi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, which death brings vs vnto, in the world to come. Here we are but members of the Church militant, where is nothing but co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating: there wee ſhall be parts of the Church tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant, where is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but reioycing. Here wee ſowe in teares, but there we ſhall reape in ioy. All the riches and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this life, are no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in compariſon of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall felicity: for no tongue created, either of Man or Angell, can ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:12333:56"/>
the ioyes of heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>; no imagination conceiue, nor vnderſtanding com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend them: for Chriſt himſelfe ſaith, <hi>Nemo ſcit, niſi qui accipiet;</hi> No man knowes them, but he that enioyes them; ſuch is the infinite value, glory, and maieſtie, of the felicity prepared for vs in heauen, (which is the accompliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of all our hope.) Thus recounting the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of this world, the mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable ſtate of this life, and the ineſtimable bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſednes of the life to come, let vs with the Apoſtles and Prophets cry:
<q>
                     <pb n="103" facs="tcp:12333:56"/>
                     <p>O miſerable man that I am, who ſhall deliuer mee from this body of death?</p>
                     <p>My ſoule thirſteth for thee, O God, when ſhall I goe, and appeare before the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the liuing God?</p>
                     <p>I deſire to be diſſolued, and to be with Chriſt.</p>
                     <p>Come quickly, Lord Ieſus, come quickly.</p>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The GOD of all power and mercie, increaſe in our hearts a deſire of this learning, that wee may liue in his feare, and die in his fauour, whereby wee may liue for euer, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="104" facs="tcp:12333:57"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 13.</hi> Againſt the loue of the world, which is the ſecond cauſe that lets vs from dying willingly.</head>
               <p>THe loue and reſpect man beares to the pleaſures and vanities of this world, is not onely of it ſelfe a ſtrong impedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and let to our wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe to death, and to the ſeruice of God; but a generall cauſe alſo, and as it were, a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon ground to all other impediments; whatſoeuer other excuſes are pretended: for when
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:12333:57"/>
the Noble men of <hi>Iewry</hi> refuſed to confeſſe Chriſt openly, Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> vttereth the true cauſe thereof to be, <hi>for that they loued the glory of man, more then the glory of GOD,</hi> Iohn <hi>chap.</hi> 12.</p>
               <p>This may be confirmed by that moſt excellent Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable of the Seed,<note place="margin">The expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition of the Para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Seed.</note> which concernes three ſorts of perſons:<note place="margin">1. High-way.</note> the firſt ſort of which, our Sauiour com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pareth to a High-way, wherein all ſeede of life that is ſowne, either withe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth preſently, or elſe is ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten vp by the birds of the Ayre; that is, by the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uels,
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:12333:58"/>
in ſuch careleſſe men, as contemne whatſoeuer is ſaid vnto them.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2 Rocky ground.</note>The ſecond ſort, are compared to Rockie grounds, in which, for lacke of deepe roote, the ſeed that falleth, continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth not: whereby are ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified light &amp; vnconſtant perſons; that now chop in, and now runne out: now are feruent, and by and by, key-cold againe; and ſo in time of temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they are gone.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">3 Good ground, but full of thornes.</note>The third ſort are com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared to a Field, wherein the ſeede of life groweth vp, but yet there are ſo
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:12333:58"/>
many thornes about the ſame (which be the cares, troubles, miſeries, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiueable vanities of this life) as the good corne is choaked vp, and bringeth forth no fruit. Where the Goſpell is preached, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued and profeſſed, and doth not fructifie in our hearts, to bring forth a vertuous life, there the ſeed is choaked with the loue &amp; care of this world: ſo that the fault is neither in the ſower, nor in the ſeede, but onely in the ground.</p>
               <p>This Parable containeth ſixe points.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:12333:59"/>
                  <note place="margin">1 How this world, and the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities thereof, are meere vanities.</note>Firſt, how, and in vvhat ſence, this world, and the vanities therof, are meere vanities in themſelues, and of no value: and therefore ought not to let vs from ſeruing of God, and from ſo great a matter, as is the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2 Decepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons.</note>Secondly, how they are not onely vanities and trifles; but alſo <hi>Deceptions,</hi> deceits, and fallacies, not performing thoſe trifles, which they doe promiſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">3 Pricking thornes.</note>Thirdly, how they are <hi>ſpinae,</hi> that is, pricking thornes, albeit to world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly men, they ſeeme to be
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:12333:59"/>
moſt ſweet and pleaſant things.</p>
               <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">4. Miſeries and afflic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> how they are <hi>Aerumnae,</hi> miſeries and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <hi>quomodo ſuffo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">5. How they do ſtrangle the poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor.</note> how they ſtrangle or choake their poſſeſſors.</p>
               <p>Sixtly,<note place="margin">6. How they are to be vſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</note> how wee may vſe them notwithſtanding without theſe dangers and euils, to our great comfort, gaine, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment.</p>
               <p>That all the pleaſures,<note place="margin">How all the plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the world are meere vanities.</note> delights, and goodly ſhewes of this world are meere vanities, is proued by the teſtimony of King <hi>Salomon,</hi> who taſted and
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:12333:60"/>
proued them all, of his own experience and prac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice: yet after all this, hee pronounced at laſt, this ſentence of it all, <hi>Vanitas vanitatum, &amp; omnia vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas:</hi> by vanity of vanities, meaning the greatneſſe of this vanity, aboue al other vanities, that may be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiſed.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> maketh an earneſt exhortation to all wiſe men, neuer to intan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle themſelues with the loue of worldly affaires: for, <hi>Mundus tranſit &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupiſcentia eius:</hi> the world is tranſitorie, and all that is to be deſired therein, is
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:12333:60"/>
vaine, vncertaine, and not permanent.</p>
               <p>This tranſitory vanity,<note place="margin">The gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of worldly vanities.</note> hee reduceth to three ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall heads or branches, ſaying, Whatſoeuer is in the world, is either, <hi>Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence of the fleſh, or concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence of the eyes, or pride of life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vnder concupiſcence of the fleſh,<note place="margin">Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence of the fleſh.</note> hee compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth all ſenſuall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, vſed in cheriſhing &amp; pampering of the fleſh.</p>
               <p>Vnder the ſecond,<note place="margin">2 Concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of the eyes.</note> all beauty and brauerie of riches.</p>
               <p>Vnder the third,<note place="margin">3 Pride of life.</note> is ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified the vanitie of Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bition,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:12333:61"/>
in worldly honour and eſtimation.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Three principall vanities.</note>Theſe are three gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall and moſt principall vanities of this life, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in worldly men do weary out their braines: to wit, <hi>Ambition,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ambition, couetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures.</note> 
                  <hi>Couetouſnes, and carnall pleaſures:</hi> Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto all leſſer vanities are addreſſed, as to their Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">To Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long theſe ſixe members.</note>To <hi>Ambition and pride of life,</hi> belong theſe ſixe members.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <hi>Vaine-glory,</hi> which is a certaine diſordinate deſire,<note place="margin">1. Vaine-glory.</note> to be well thought of, well ſpoken of, praiſed, and glorified of men.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:12333:61"/>What a vanity, what a miſery is this, to depend on other mens mouthes: to caſt thy trauels into the winde of mens mouthes, where euery flatterer may rob thee of them?</p>
               <p>It is a miſerable thing, for a man to bee a wind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mill, which grindeth not but as the blaſt endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth: ſo praiſe the vaine-glorious man, &amp; ye make him runne; if he feele not the gale blow, he is out of heart. How many haue wee ſeene puffed vp with mens praiſes, and almoſt put beſides themſelues for ioy thereof? who after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:12333:62"/>
being brought downe with a contrarie wind, haue beene driuen in a maner to deſperation by contempt.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">1 Worldly honour and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion.</note>The ſecond vanity that belongeth to ambition, is deſire of worldly honour, dignity, and promotion. This is a great matter in the ſight of a worldly man: this is a iewell of rare price, and worthy to be bought with any la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, trauell, or perill whatſoeuer: the loue of this, letteth infinite men daily, from embracing the meanes of their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="115" facs="tcp:12333:62"/>
                  <hi>Nolite eſse puert ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus:</hi> Be you not children in vnderſtanding. It is the faſhion of children, to eſteeme more of a pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted bable, then of a rich iewell. And ſuch is the painted dignity of this world, gotten with much labour, maintained with great expenſes, and loſt with intolerable griefe &amp; ſorrow. For better con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiuing whereof, ponder with thy ſelfe any ſtate of dignity, that thou would<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt deſire, and thinke how many haue had that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee: and what are now become of all thoſe
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:12333:63"/>
great Emperours, Kings, Princes, and Prelates, which reioyced ſo much at their aduancement? Who talketh, or thinketh of them now? Are they not forgotten, and caſt into their graues long agoe? And doe not men walke boldly ouer their heads now, whoſe faces might not be looked on, without feare in their life? What then, haue their dignities done them good?</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſo much de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed worldly honour in this life, as that hee made leſſe account thereof, then
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:12333:63"/>
of common dung.</p>
               <p>Moſt vaine then, is the purſuite of this worldly honour, which neither contenteth the minde, nor eaſeth the pained body, nor continueth with the poſſeſſour, nor leaueth behind it, any benefit or contentation.</p>
               <p>The third vanity that belongeth to <hi>Ambition</hi> or <hi>pride of life,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">3 The vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of worldly Nobility.</note> is Nobility of fleſh and blood: a great pearle in the eye of the world, but in deed, and in it ſelfe, and in the ſight of God, a meere trifle &amp; va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. Which <hi>Iob</hi> well vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, when hee ſaid,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:12333:64"/>
                  <hi>I ſaid vnto rottennes, Thou art my father; and vnto wormes, You are my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and ſisters.</hi> Hee that will behold the Gentry of his anceſtours, let him looke into their graues, and ſee whether <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith true or no.</p>
               <p>True Nobility was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer begun but by vertue, and therefore as it is a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonie of vertue in the predeceſſours: ſo ought it to be a ſpurre to vertue in the ſucceſſours: And hee which holdeth the name thereof by deſcent only, without vertue, is a meere monſter in reſpect
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:12333:64"/>
of his anceſtours: for that he breaketh the limits and nature of Nobility: ſuch haue their glory onely from their natiuity, <hi>from the belly, and from their conception.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is a miſerable vanity to begge credit of dead men, whereas we deſerue none our ſelues: to ſeeke vp old titles of honour from our anceſtours, wee being vtterly vncapable thereof, by our owne baſe manners and behauiours: to ſeeke vp this and that old title of honour, to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh his ſtile withall, is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry idle and baſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="120" facs="tcp:12333:65"/>
                  <note place="margin">4. The vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of worldly wiſedome.</note>The fourth vanity to Ambition or pride of life, is <hi>worldly wiſdome:</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>The wiſedome of this world is folly with God.</hi> If it be folly, then great vanity, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light and boaſt ſo much in it, as men doe.</p>
               <p>The faſhion of worldly wiſe men, is, to condemne the wiſedome of God, till againſt their wills they be forced to cry: <hi>Nos inſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſati vitam illorum eſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bamus inſaniam:</hi> We fond men eſteemed the liues of Saints, as madneſſe. Vaine then and of no account, is the wiſedome of this
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:12333:65"/>
world, except it be ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect to the Wiſedome of God.</p>
               <p>The fifth vanity belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to pride of life,<note place="margin">5. The va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of beauty.</note> is cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall beauty, whereof the wiſe man ſaith, <hi>Vaine is beauty, and deceiueable is the grace of a faire counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</hi> Which <hi>Dauid</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood well enough, when he ſaid, <hi>Turne away my eyes, O Lord, that they behold not vanity.</hi> This is a ſingular great vanity, dangerous and deceitfull: but yet greatly eſteemed of the children of men, whoſe property is to loue vanity: but he that remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:12333:66"/>
what foule droſſe lies vnder a faire skinne, will bee little in loue there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>with.</p>
               <p>GOD hath imparted certaine ſparkles of beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty vnto his creatures, ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by to draw vs to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration and loue of his owne beauty, whereof the other is but a ſhadow: from whence in deede all creatures doe deriue their beauty.</p>
               <p>What can be more va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity then this? what more madneſſe, then either to take a pride thereof, if wee haue it our ſelues, or to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger our ſoules for the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:12333:66"/>
ſame, if wee behold it in others?</p>
               <p>The ſixt vanity belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to pride of life,<note place="margin">6 Vanity of Apparell.</note> is the glory of fine apparell: againſt which the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, <hi>In veſtitu ne gloriaris vnquam.</hi> Neuer take pride and glory in apparell: for that is, as if a begger ſhould glory and take pride of the old clouts, that doe couer his ſores.</p>
               <p>The ſecond generall head of worldly vanities,<note place="margin">Concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of the eyes.</note> is, <hi>Concupiſcence of the eyes,</hi> whereunto are referred all vanities of riches and wealth of this world.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="124" facs="tcp:12333:67"/>Of this, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth to <hi>Timothy: Giue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement to the rich men of this world, not to be high-minded, nor to put confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the vncertainty of their riches; for, riches ſhall not profit a man in the day of reuenge,</hi> that is, at the day of death and Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Which doth eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently declare the great vanity of worldly riches, which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> do the poſſeſſor no good at al, whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he hath moſt need of their helpe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rich men haue ſlept their ſleepe, and haue found no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in their hands:</hi> that is, rich men haue paſſed
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:12333:67"/>
ouer this life, as men doe a ſleepe, imagining them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to haue golden mountaines and treaſures, wherewith to helpe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues, in all needes that ſhall occurre: and when they awake (at the day of their death) they finde themſelues to haue no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing in their hands that can doe them good.</p>
               <p>In reſpect whereof, the Prophet <hi>Baruch</hi> asketh this queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, <hi>Where are they now, which heaped together gold and ſiluer, and which made no end of their ſcra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping together?</hi> &amp; he anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth himſelfe immediatly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="126" facs="tcp:12333:68"/>
                  <hi>Exterminati ſunt et ad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feros deſcenderunt,</hi> they are now rooted out, and are gone downe vnto hell. To like effect ſaith Saint <hi>Iames, Now ye rich men, doe you weepe and wayle, and howle in your miſeries that come vpon you: your riches are rotten, and your gold and ſiluer is ruſtie: and the ruſt thereof ſhall be in teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monie againſt you; it ſhall feede vpon your owne fleſh, as if it were fire: you haue hoorded vp wrath to your owne ſelues in the laſt day.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>If wealth then bee not onely ſo vaine, but alſo ſo perillous, what vanity is it
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:12333:68"/>
for men, to ſet their minds ſo vpon it? which S. <hi>Paul</hi> eſteemed no better, then as the dung of the earth. What a baſe thing is it for a man, to tye his loue thereunto: and to glew his heart and ſoule vnto a piece of earth?</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Wee came naked into the world, and naked wee muſt goe forth againe: when the rich man dieth, he ſhall take nothing with him: but ſhall cloze vp his eyes and finde nothing: neither ſhall his glory deſcend to the place, whither he goeth.</hi> Dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous then is the vanity of worldly wealth, and great
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:12333:69"/>
is the folly of thoſe men, which labour ſo much to procure the ſame, with the eternall perils of their ſoules. <hi>Qui diligit aurum, non iuſtificabitur: Woe be to you rich men, for you haue receiued your conſolation in this life.</hi> Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith generally of all, and to all, <hi>They which will be rich, doe fall into temptations; and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſnares of Satan, and into many vnprofitable and hurtfull deſires, which doe drowne them in euerlasting deſtruction and perdition.</hi> What can be more effec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually ſpoken, to diſſwade from the loue of riches?</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="129" facs="tcp:12333:69"/>Many excuſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſelues by the pretence of Wife and Children,<note place="margin">The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Wife and Children refuted.</note> and that they doe but prouide for their ſufficiency. As if where Gods ſeruice and their own ſaluation com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth in queſtion, Chriſt would admit any ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe? Ought we to loue wife or children ſo much, as to endanger our ſoules for them? What co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort can it bee to an afflicted father in Hell, to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber that by his meanes, his wife and children liue wealthily in earth, and that for his eternall woe, they enioy ſome few yeres
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:12333:70"/>
pleaſure. This is a vanity and a meere deceit of our ſpirituall enemy: for within one moment after we are dead, wee ſhall no more care for Wife and Children, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> for a meere ſtranger. When death comes, then are we to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part to that place where fleſh and bloud holdeth no more priuiledge, nor riches haue any power to deliuer.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">3 Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence of the fleſh.</note>The third Branch of worldly vanities, is, <hi>Concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence of the fleſh,</hi> which containeth all worldly pleaſures, and carnall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations of this life.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="131" facs="tcp:12333:70"/>
                  <hi>Woe be vnto you, that now liue in fill and ſacietie; for the time ſhall come, when you ſhall ſuffer hunger.</hi> Chriſt ſpeaking to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, and by them to all other, ſaith, <hi>You ſhall weepe and mourne, but the world ſhall reioyce,</hi> making it a ſigne diſiunctiue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene the good and the bad: that the one ſhall mourne in this life, and the other reioyce &amp; make themſelues merry. In re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect whereof, we are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led to paſſe ouer this life in carefulneſſe, watchful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, feare &amp; trembling. <hi>Sollicitum ambulare cum
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:12333:71"/>
Deo.</hi> To walke carefully, and diligently with God. <hi>Beatus homo qui ſemper eſt pauidus:</hi> happy is the man, which is alwayes fearefull. <hi>Riſus dolore miſcebitur, &amp; extrema gaudii luctus occu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>;</hi> laughter ſhall bee mingled with ſorrow, and mourning ſhall enſue at the latter end of mirth.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Vniuerſa vanitas, omnis homo viuens:</hi> the life of ſuch worldly-minded me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, containeth all kinde of va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity: that is to ſay, vanity in Ambition; vanity in ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; vanity in pleaſures; vanity in all things they moſt eſteeme: therefore
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:12333:71"/>
                  <hi>Vae vobis, qui trahitis ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quitatem in funiculis vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatis:</hi> Woe vnto you that doe draw iniquitie in the ropes of vanitie. Theſe ropes, are thoſe vanities of vaine-glory, Promoti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Dignity, Nobilitie, Beauty, riches &amp; delights, which alwayes draw with them ſome iniquity and ſinne. <hi>Beatus vir qui non reſpexit in vanitates &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanias falſas.</hi> Bleſſed is the man, that hath not reſpec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vanities, and the falſe madneſſe of this world.</p>
               <p>The ſecond part of the Parable ſheweth,<note place="margin">How worldly vanities are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits.</note> how this world, with the commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:12333:72"/>
thereof, are not onely vanities, but alſo de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceits: for that indeed they doe not performe vnto their followers, thoſe idle vanities and trifles, which they doe promiſe.</p>
               <p>Can there be a greater deceit, then to promiſe renowne (as the world doth to her followers) and to forget them as ſoone as they are dead? Who now remembreth one of 10000. iolly fellowes, that haue beene in this world? who once thinks or ſpeaks of them now? hath not their memory periſhed with their ſound, as the
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:12333:72"/>
Prophet foretold? Did not <hi>Iob</hi> promiſe truely, that, <hi>their remembrance ſhould bee, as aſhes troden vnder foote?</hi> and <hi>Dauid, that they ſhould bee as duſt, blowne abroad with the winde?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Infinite are the deceits and diſſimulations of the world. It ſeemeth goodly, faire and gorgeous in outward ſhew: but when it commeth to handling, it is nothing but a feather: when it commeth to ſight, it is nothing but a ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow: when it commeth to weight, it is nothing but ſmoake: when it com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:12333:73"/>
to opening, it is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but an Image of plaiſter-worke; full of old rags and patches within. O miſerable and moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceitfull world, ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine!</hi> whoſe ſorrows are certaine, and pleaſures vncertaine: whoſe paines are permanent, and repoſe tranſitorie: whoſe toyles are intolerable, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards moſt contempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble: whoſe promiſes are princely, and paiments beggerly: whoſe miſeries are void of all conſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and whoſe happineſſe is mingled with all kinde of miſery. It hates them,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:12333:73"/>
that loue it: deceiues them that truſt it: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicts them, that ſerue it: reproacheth them, that honour it: damnes them, that followe it: and ſoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt of all forgets them, that labour moſt of all for it: vpon great cauſe then ſaid the Prophet <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid, O you children of men, how long will yee bee ſo dull hearted! Why doe you loue vanity, and ſeeke after a lye?</hi> He calleth the world, not a lyer, but a lye it ſelfe, for the exceeding great fraud and deciet which it vſeth.<note place="margin">How plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of the world are thorns</note>
               </p>
               <p>How pleaſures of the world, are <hi>Thornes,</hi> for
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:12333:74"/>
that, with the prickes of their carefull cogitations, they teare and make blou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy the mindes of worldly men: for euen as a mans naked body, toſſed and tumbled among Thornes, cannot but bee torne and made bloudy with the prickes thereof: ſo a worldly mans ſoule, bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with the cares and co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitations of this life, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but bee vexed vvith reſtleſſe pricking of the ſame, and wounded alſo with many temptations of ſinne which doe occurre. This doth <hi>Salomon</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie, when he doth not only
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:12333:74"/>
call the riches and plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures of this world, <hi>Vanity of vanities,</hi> that is, the greateſt of all other vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties: but alſo affliction of ſpirit.</p>
               <p>Of all the miſeries and vexations that God layeth vpon worldlings, this is not the leaſt, to bee tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented with the cares of that thing, which they e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteeme their greateſt feli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citie. Which notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding like an vnmercifull tyrant, giues them no reſt either by day or by night.</p>
               <p>The fourth point of the Parable: how this word,<note place="margin">Miſery and cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie.</note> 
                  <hi>Aerumna,</hi> that is, miſery &amp;
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:12333:75"/>
calamitie, may be verified of the world, and of the felicitie thereof.</p>
               <p>Among many other miſeries, the firſt, and one of the greateſt,<note place="margin">1. Breuitie.</note> is the bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitie and vncertaintie of all worldly proſperitie. O how great a miſery is this vnto a worldly man, that would haue his pleaſures conſtant, and perpetuall! <hi>O death, how bitter is the remembrance of thee, vnto a man that hath peace in his riches!</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">2 Diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentment.</note>Another miſery ioyned to the proſperitie of this world, is the grieuous counterpoiſe of diſcon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentments,
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:12333:75"/>
that euery worldly pleaſure hath with it.</p>
               <p>The poſſeſſion of riches,<note place="margin">Riches.</note> is accompanied with infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite feares and cares.</p>
               <p>The aduancement of honours,<note place="margin">Honour.</note> is ſubiect to all miſerable ſeruitude, that may be deuiſed.</p>
               <p>The pleaſure of the fleſh,<note place="margin">Pleaſure.</note> though it be lawfull and honeſt, is yet accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>panied with tribulation of the fleſh: but if it be with ſinne, a thouſand times more it is inuironed with all kinde of miſeries:<note place="margin">3 Miſeries of body.</note> who can reckon vp the calami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of our body? ſo many
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:12333:76"/>
diſeaſes, ſo many infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, ſo many miſchances, ſo many dangers?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of minde.</note>Who can tell the paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of our minde, that do afflict vs; now with ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, now with enuy, now with fury?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of goods.</note>Who can recount the aduerſities &amp; misfortunes that come by our goods?</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Of neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours.</note>Who can number the hurts and diſcontentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, that dayly enſue vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on vs from our neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours? one calleth vs into Law for our goods: an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other purſues vs for our life: a third by ſlander im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pugneth our good name:
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:12333:76"/>
ſo that, there are not ſo many dayes, nor houres in our liues, as there are miſeries and contrarieties in the ſame. And more then this;<note place="margin">The pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue of euill.</note> the euill hath this prerogatiue aboue the good in our life, that one defect onely ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmeth and drowneth a great number of plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures together: As if a man had all the felicities heaped together, which this world could yeeld, and yet had but one tooth out of tune, all the other pleaſures would not make him merry. GOD ſhall raine ſnares vpon ſinfull
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:12333:77"/>
men, <hi>Pluet ſuper eos laqueos:</hi> that is, God ſhall permit wicked men to fall into ſnares, which are as plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull in the world, as drops of raine from hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions and dangers.</note>Euery man almoſt is a deadly ſnare vnto a car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall &amp; looſe-hearted man: euery ſight that he ſeeth: euery word that hee hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth: euery thought that he conceiueth, &amp;c. all are ſnares to draw him to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction, that is not watchfull.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Facility of ſinning.</note>The laſt, and greateſt miſery of all others in this life, is, the facilitie, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:12333:77"/>
worldly men do runne into ſinne, and make no ſcruple of the matter, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, <hi>Bibit quaſi aquam, iniquitatem,</hi> hee ſuppeth vp ſinne, as it were water, that is, with great facility, cuſtome and eaſe, aduen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tureth hee vpon any kinde of ſinne that is offered him, as a man drinketh water when hee is a thirſt.</p>
               <p>The fifth point of the Parable:<note place="margin">How the world choketh &amp; ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth vs.</note> how the loue of the world choketh and ſtrangleth euery man whom it poſſeſſeth, from all celeſtiall and ſpirituall life: for that it filleth him with a plaine contrarie
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:12333:78"/>
ſpirit, to the Spirit of God. <hi>Si quis Spiritum Chriſti non habet, hic non est eius:</hi> If any haue not the Spirit of Chriſt, that man belongs not vnto him. The effects of the Spirit, are Charitie, Ioy, Peace, Patience, &amp;c. The effects of the ſpirit of the world, are fornication, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleaneneſſe, wantonneſſe, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Whoſo deſireth to bee a friend of this world, is thereby made an enemy to God: therefore, <hi>nolite conformari huic ſeculo: no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite diligere mundum, neque ea quae in mundo ſunt:</hi> ſo
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:12333:78"/>
that wee may neither loue it, nor conforme our ſelues vnto it, vnder the paine of the enmitie of God, and of eternall dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation. Seeing then this world is ſuch a thing as it is; ſo vaine, ſo deceitfull, ſo troubleſome, ſo dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous; who would bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued, or allured with the vanity thereof, or bee ſtayed from the noble ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uice of God, by the loue of ſo fond a trifle as is this world?<note place="margin">How we may auoid the dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers of the world.</note>
               </p>
               <p>The ſixt point of this Parable, how wee may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoid the dangers of the world, and vſe them to our
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:12333:79"/>
owne gaine &amp; commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. The onely way, is, to vſe the refuge of birds, in auoiding the dangerous ſnares of Fowlers, that is, to mount vp into the aire, and ſo to fly ouer them al: <hi>Frustrà iacitur rete, ante o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culos pennatorum,</hi> the net is laid in vaine, before the eyes of ſuch as haue wings and can fly. And as the Fowler hath no hope to catch the bird, except hee can allure her to pitch and to come downe: ſo hath the Diuell no way to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tangle vs, but to ſay, as he ſaid to Chriſt, <hi>Mitte te de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orſum,</hi> throwe thy ſelfe
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:12333:79"/>
downe vpon the baites which I haue laid: eat and deuoure them, enamour thy ſelfe with them, tye thine appetite vnto them, and the like: which groſſe and open temptation, hee that will auoid, by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temning the allurements of theſe baits, by flying o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer them, by placing his loue &amp; cogitations in the mountaines of heauenly ioyes &amp; eternity: hee ſhall eaſily eſcape all dangers and perils. S. <hi>Paul</hi> paſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer theſe dangers, when he ſaid, <hi>that he was now crucifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to the world, &amp; the world vnto him;</hi> and that <hi>he eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:12333:80"/>
all the wealth of this world, as meere dung:</hi> and albeit he liued in the fleſh, yet liued he not according to the fleſh. Which glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious example if we would follow, in contemning &amp; deſpiſing the vanities of this world, and fixing our minds on the noble riches of Gods eternal Kingdom to come: the ſnares of the Diuell would preuaile no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing at all againſt vs in this life. Now how to vſe the riches and commodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of this world to our aduantage, Chriſt hath plainely laid downe the meanes, ſaying, <hi>Facite vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:12333:80"/>
amicos de Mammona iniquitatis:</hi> Make vnto you friends of the riches of iniquitie. How eaſily then, may rich men bee happy, if they will? &amp; what a plentifull harueſt may they reape to themſelues, if they were wiſe, hauing ſuch ſtore of ſeed by them, and ſo much ground of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fred them dayly to ſow it in? <hi>O you rich men,</hi> therefore, <hi>deceiue not your ſelues; for what a man ſow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that ſhall hee reape,</hi> Rom.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="152" facs="tcp:12333:81"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 14. 14</hi> Againſt procraſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</head>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
                  <note place="margin">Our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſion is made harder by delay.</note>LEt vs turn to the Lord, and put not off from day to day: for many in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conueniences inſue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craſtination. If wee doe ſleepe in ſecurity, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtome our ſelues with ſinning, our cuſtome will wax to be our nature, and hard will it be to riſe from ſinne, in which wee haue been ſo long and ſo deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly buried: for continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of ſinne bringeth cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome,
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:12333:81"/>
which hauing got<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten roote in vs, will hardly be rooted out of vs.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondy, the longer we perſiſt in our ſinfull life, the further off is Gods helpe from vs, and the more doth hee plucke his grace and aſſiſtance from vs: for by delay, wee ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſperate Gods iuſtice, and heape vengeance on our owne heads.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, by longer cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of ſinne, the habit is more deepely rooted in vs: and the power and kingdome of the deuill more eſtabliſhed &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed in vs: our minde
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:12333:82"/>
more infected: our iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment more weakened: our good deſires extingui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed: our paſſions con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed: our body corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted: our ſtrength dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, and all our whole Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-wealth the more peruerted.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, it is dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, in reſpect of the ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den taking away of man, who is often ſo ſuddenly ſmitten, that hee hath no time to thinke vpon God, much leſſe to call vpon him with true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> The fifth danger is, that in driuing off to the laſt
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:12333:82"/>
houre, we ſhall finde hard time then to turne vnto God: for ſicknes will ſore diſquiet vs: Satan will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tremely tempt vs: Friends with talking and crauing will moleſt vs: the terrour of our vgly conſcience will aſtoniſh vs: ſo that it will bee very hard to be rightly mindfull of our end, and in our extremity to call to God for mercy.</p>
               <p>Miſerable is that ſoule, which placeth the ankor of his eternall wealth or woe, vpon ſo tickle a point, as is his conuerſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on at the very laſt houre. It is ſaid to be tickle, in
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:12333:83"/>
regard all Diuines ſpeake very doubtfully of it: and albeit they doe not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely condemne it in all, but doe leaue it as vncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine vnto Gods ſecret iudgement: yet doe they encline vnto the negatiue part, and do alledge foure reaſons.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt, for that the extreme feare and paines of death, which are moſt terrible, doe not permit a man commonly, ſo to ga-gather his ſpirits and ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces at that time, as is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired, for the treating of ſo weighty a matter with Almighty God, as is our
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:12333:83"/>
conuerſion and ſaluation: for ſcarcely can any fixe his minde earneſtly vpon heauenly cogitations at ſuch time, as hee is but troubled with the paſſions of Chollick or Stone, or other ſharp diſeaſes: how much leſſe in the angui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes of death.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The ſecond is, for that the conuerſion which a man makes at the laſt day, is not for the moſt part voluntary, but vpon ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsity, and for feare.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> The third reaſon, for that the cuſtome of ſinne cannot be remoued vpon the inſtant, being growne
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:12333:84"/>
now (as it were) into na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelfe: for which cauſe God ſaith to euill men by the Prophet <hi>Iere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie: If an Aethiopian can change his blacke skin, or a Leopard his ſpots, then can you alſo doe well, hauing lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned all dayes of your life to doe euill?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> The fourth cauſe is, for that the acts of Vertue themſelues cannot be of ſo great value with God in that inſtant, as if they had beene done in time of health before: for what great matter is it, then to pardon thine enemie, when thou canſt hurt him
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:12333:84"/>
no more? To giue thy goods away, when thou canſt enioy them no lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger? To abandon thy Concubine, when of force thou muſt forſake her? To leaue to ſinne, when ſinne leaueth thee? He is a care<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe and a graceleſſe man, who knowing all this, will venture notwithſtanding the eternitie of his ſaluati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and damnation, vpon the doubtfull euent of his finall repentance. But what ingratitude and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtice is this towards Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, hauing re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiued ſo many benefits from him already, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting
<pb n="160" facs="tcp:12333:85"/>
ſo great a mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter hereafter, as is the Kingdome of Heauen: to appoint out the leaſt, laſt, and worſt part of thy life vnto his ſeruice: and that whereof thou art moſt vncertaine, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it ſhall euer bee or neuer; or whether God will accept it or no. What Law, iuſtice, or equitie is this, that after thou haſt ſerued the World, Fleſh and Diuell, all thy youth and beſt dayes; in the end to come &amp; thruſt thine old bones, defiled and worne out with ſinne, into the diſh of thy Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor:
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:12333:85"/>
his enemies to haue the beſt, and hee the lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uings? The onely way therefore to eſcape this dangerous and vncertaine point, is,<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eſay</hi> 55.</note> to conuert in time: <hi>to ſeeke vnto GOD while hee may bee found; to call vpon him, while hee is neere at hand.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 15.</hi> Againſt miſtruſt in Gods mercy.</head>
               <p>THis is that great and maine impediment, that ſtoppeth the conduits <gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:12333:86"/>
Gods holy grace, from flowing into the Soule of a ſinfull man: for there cannot bee a greater diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour to GOD, nor any thing more diſplea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to him, then to doubt of his mercy, whoſe heart is more tender towards vs, then the heart of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mother can bee to the onely childe and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fant of her wombe: for thus hee ſaith to Sion, which for her ſinnes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ganne to doubt, leaſt hee had forſaken her: <hi>Can the mother forget her owne infant? or can ſhee not bee mercifull to the child of her
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:12333:86"/>
owne wombe? If ſhee could, yet can I not forget or reiect thee: behold, I haue writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten thee in the fleſh of mine owne hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As the Father pittieth his owne children, ſo doth the Lord take mercy vpon vs: hee knoweth whereof we be made, hee remembreth that we are but duſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God will not deſpiſe the worke of his owne hands.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I am hee, I am he</hi> (ſaith the LORD) <hi>that for mine owne ſake will doe away thine offences, and will no more thinke of thy ſinnes,</hi> Eſay 43.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>As ſurely as I liue, I
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:12333:87"/>
will not thy death, but ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that thou ſhalt be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerted and liue,</hi> Ezech. 33.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Nunquid voluntatis meae eſt, mors impit?</hi> Haue I any pleaſure in the death of a ſinner? ſaith the Lord. GOD, by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet <hi>Ieremy,</hi> complai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth grieuouſly, <hi>Eſay</hi> 1. that men will not accept of his mercy offered, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Turne from your wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked wayes, why will yee dye, O you houſe of Iſrael?</hi> GOD <hi>ſo loued the world, that hee gaue his onely be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten Sonne to the death to redeeme vs,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Special ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments of Gods exceeding loue.</note> 
                  <hi>that who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer beleeueth in him,
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:12333:87"/>
ſhould not periſh, but haue life euerlaſting:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">The ſum of the Goſpell.</note> 
                  <hi>hereun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all the Prophets beare witneſse, that whoſoeuer ſhall beleeue in him, by his name, hee ſhall haue re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsion of ſinnes, and withall eternall life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>God gaue his Sonne to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme vs, euen then when wee were his enemies: and if when wee were his ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, wee were reconciled vnto GOD, by the death of his Sonne; much more being reconciled, ſhall we be ſaued by his life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Chriſt came not into the world, to condemne the world, but to ſaue it: hee
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:12333:88"/>
came not to call the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but ſinners to repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 16.</hi> The promiſes of God to ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that repent, are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifold, abſolute, and vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſall.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VVHoſoeuer ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from his euill wayes, and turne vnto mee</hi> (ſaith the Lord) <hi>I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him.</hi> Behold here the the vniuerſality of all peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple and perſons, without excluding any.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>At what time ſoeuer a
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:12333:88"/>
ſinner, doth repent him of his ſinne, from the bottome of his heart, I will put away all his wickedneſse out of my remembrance</hi> (ſaith the Lord:) ſee the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalitie of all times and ſeaſons vvithout excep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Leaue off to doe peruerſly, and then doe you come and finde fault with mee, if you can: For if your ſinnes were as red as Scarlet, they ſhall be made as white as Snow.</hi> Conſider here the vniuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalitie of all kind of ſinnes, bee they neuer ſo grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uous, ſo horrible, or hai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="168" facs="tcp:12333:89"/>As nothing doth more exaſperate theyre of God, then the depriuing of his Maieſty of that moſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent propertie, wherein he chiefly delighteth and gloryeth, which is, his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite and vnſpeakeable mercy: ſo nothing doth more aſſure vs of Gods mercy &amp; fauour towards vs, then that he is our Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ator and Father: which two words, the one of loue, the other of power, takes away all doubt of beeing denied any thing, that wee ſhall aske in his name, with <hi>Faith.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This bleſſed name of
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:12333:89"/>
                  <hi>Father</hi> (in God) doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port vnto vs, by his owne teſtimonie, all ſweetneſſe, all loue, all comfort, all fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therly prouidence, care and protection: all cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintie of fauour, all aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of grace, all ſecurity of mercy, pardon and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of our ſins, when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer vnfainedly we turn vnto him: for neuer ſinner repented, that was not pardoned; neuer any that returned vnfainedly, that was not mercifully accep<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ted.</p>
               <p>Three things there are (ſaith S. <hi>Bernard</hi>) wherein my hope conſiſteth, and
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:12333:90"/>
whereby it is made in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uincible.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>1</hi> Charitas vocationis.</note> Firſt, in the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding loue and charitie of him, that calleth vs to him by repentance.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>2</hi> Veritas pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſsionis.</note> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, the infallible truth and certainty of his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, which he maketh to vs of pardon and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>3.</hi> Poteſtas redditionis.</note> Thirdly, the endleſſe power and abilitie hee hath, to performe whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer he promiſeth. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore if thou beeſt ready to breathe out thy ſoule and Spirit, feare not to repent: for Gods mercy is not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrained, by the ſhortneſſe of time.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="171" facs="tcp:12333:90"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 17.</hi> How one ſhould demeane himſelfe, when ſickneſſe beginneth.</head>
               <p>THe firſt and principall thing religiouſly to bee remembred in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of ſickneſſe, is, that the ſoule doe call her ſelfe to a ſerious account of ſinnes paſſed, of the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill committed, and the good omitted, remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring that of the Prophet, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 32.9. <hi>I will confeſse a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt my ſelfe mine owne vnrighteouſneſse.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In all extremities, our
<pb n="172" facs="tcp:12333:91"/>
chiefeſt care ought to be, by Prayer to call vpon God for helpe, and religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly to commend our ſelues and ſoules vnto God.</p>
               <p>A ioyfull lifting vp of the heart to the Throne of grace, makes vs willing to renounce the world; and to reſigne our ſelues ouer vnto his diuine plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, to whoſe will wee ought with patience, meekely to ſubmit our ſelues, both for our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance in this life, and for our deliuerance out of this life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="173" facs="tcp:12333:91"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 18.</hi> The diſpoſing of bleſsings temporall.</head>
               <p>HIs ſinnes by the ſicke partie confeſſed: his ſoule religiouſly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to GOD: his deſire to liue or die, refer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to the diuine proui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence: an orderly diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of thoſe temporall bleſſings, which God hath lent vs, is very conuenient for euery Chriſtian (ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in time of health:) and nothing ominous, as ſome haue timorouſly doubted. This diſpoſing
<pb n="174" facs="tcp:12333:92"/>
of bleſſings temporal, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth vs not to dye the more quickly, but the more quietly.</p>
               <p>Wee ſhew our thanke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe to God, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie to men, when we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come beneficiall vnto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, remembring whoſe ſaying it was: <hi>It is a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thing to giue,</hi> Acts 20. Then is he with a free and willing minde to yeeld and render his ſoule into the hands of Almightie God his Creator, who of his infinite mercy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed him by the death and Paſsion of his deare Sonne Ieſus Chriſt our
<pb n="175" facs="tcp:12333:92"/>
onely Sauiour and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer: in whoſe onely merits is his laſt repoſe at parting. And ſo, laying a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide all earthly reſpects, as hauing now no more to doe with the things vnder the Sunne, to commend his body to Chriſtian bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riall, and his ſoule to his mercifull Redeemer.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <pb n="176" facs="tcp:12333:93"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 19.</hi> It is neceſſary for the ſicke, after an orderly diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of his worldly goods, and leauing all worldly thoughts, to apply his mind to Prayer and god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Meditations.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Prayer.</note>THe ſweeteſt incenſe wee can offer, is our deuotion by Prayer.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The lifting vp of our hands, will be as an euening ſacrifice: he healeth our ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, and forgiueth all our ſinnes,</hi> Pſal. 103.</p>
               <p>God lookes that wee ſhould ſend vp our pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="177" facs="tcp:12333:93"/>
to him, that he might ſend downe his mercy to vs.</p>
               <p>Prayer in time of trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, is commanded with a promiſe: <hi>Call vpon mee</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>in the time of trouble, and I will heare thee, and thou ſhalt glorifie me,</hi> Pſal. 50.15.</p>
               <p>Pſalmes in time of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fliction, haue a ſpeciall &amp; peculiar grace to moue deuotion.</p>
               <p>Proper and peculiar Pſalmes for the ſicke.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Put mee not to rebuke, O Lord,</hi> Pſal. 38.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Haue mercy vpon me, O Lord,</hi> Pſal. 51.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="178" facs="tcp:12333:94"/>
                  <hi>Hast thee to deliuer mee, O God,</hi> Pſal. 70.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In thee, O Lord, haue I put my truſt,</hi> Pſal. 71.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>I will cry vnto the Lord with my voice,</hi> Pſal. 77.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Out of the deepe haue I called vnto thee, O Lord, Lord, heare my voice,</hi> Pſal. 130.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> In his meditations, let him meditate vpon the ioyes of Heauen,<note place="margin">Medita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</note> touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing which, no tongue cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated either of Man or Angel can expreſſe them, no imagination conceiue, nor vnderſtanding com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend them: for Chriſt himſelfe ſaith, <hi>Nemo ſcit,
<pb n="179" facs="tcp:12333:94"/>
niſi qui accipiet:</hi> No man knowes them, but he that enioyes them; ſuch is the infinite value, glory, and Maieſtie of the felicitie prepared for vs in heauen.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, to call to minde the vnſpeakeable loue of GOD towards man in generall, as that, <hi>God ſo loued the world, that hee gaue his onely begotten Sonne to the death, to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme vs, euen then, when wee were his enemies: and if when we were his enemies wee were reconciled vnto God, by the Death of his Son; much more being reconciled, ſhal we be ſaued by his life.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="180" facs="tcp:12333:95"/>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, to call to mind the vnſpeakeable loue of God towards our ſelues in particular, both in our Creation, Redemption, Sanctification and Iuſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Fourthly, to meditate vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the Paſſion of Chriſt, namely, how hee ſuffered the death of the Croſſe with extreme reproch and contumely: beſides moſt grieuous torments both in ſoule and body, that he might to the vtmoſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the puniſhment due to our ſinnes: Feare not, therefore (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>feare not thy ſinnes, for I am
<pb n="181" facs="tcp:12333:95"/>
the remiſsion of ſinnes: feare not darknes, I am the light: feare not death, I am the life: whoſoeuer commeth to me, ſhall neuer ſee death.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> Fifthly, to meditate vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on his deſcending into Hell: how that in his ſoule hee ſuffered ſuch ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme and fearefull tor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and euerlaſting pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhments, as that by a lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call deſcending into hell, he could not poſſibly haue indured more.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="6"/> Sixtly, to meditate vpon Chriſts Reſurrection: how by his riſing againe, hee ouercame Death, Hell, Sinne, and the Diuel him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe;
<pb n="182" facs="tcp:12333:96"/>
and ſo by his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, hee triumphed ouer Death, cloathed vs with his Righteouſneſſe, reconciled vs to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and made vs heires of his euerlaſting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="7"/> Laſtly, to meditate vpon the Aſcenſion of Chriſt; how that he is gone vp to Heauen with great glory, thereby to open a way for vs, againſt our ſelues come to poſſeſſe it after death, and body and ſoule toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, after the Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</p>
               <p>It is nothing that wee doe ſuffer, in reſpect of
<pb n="183" facs="tcp:12333:96"/>
that, which Chriſt ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red for vs: for whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer we ſuffer, Chriſt ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered more for vs: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore there is nothing, that can bee too much or too deare, for vs to beſtow vpon Chriſt.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 20.</hi> To viſit the ſicke, is a high worke of mercy.</head>
               <p>THat care is thought of greateſt impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, which is imployed in helping thoſe, who are leaſt able to helpe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues: and yet haue moſt
<pb n="184" facs="tcp:12333:97"/>
need of ghoſtly direction: this duty ſpecially con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernes them, to whom God hath committed the charge of ſoules: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is greatly to bee wiſhed, that like as the Serpent, that old enemy of mankinde, who the ſhorter his time is, the fiercer his wrath is, and himſelfe the more buſie: ſo thoſe who ſhould feed Chriſts Lambes, would now be the more carefull to keepe them from this deuouring Lyon: and to preſent them ſound in Faith, and ioyfull in hope, vnto the great Shepheard
<pb n="185" facs="tcp:12333:97"/>
of their ſoules: which is done, partly by exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, partly by Prayer.</p>
               <p>Tediouſneſſe of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe, may ſoone weary the weake party:<note place="margin">In exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> theſe things are to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued.</note> few words well ordered, auaile moſt: impertinent ſpeeches are very vnfit: a premedita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted exhortation, after in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation taken of the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of the ſicke, is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry behoouefull.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="chapter">
               <pb n="186" facs="tcp:12333:98"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 21.</hi> A Prayer at the firſt viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of the Sicke.</head>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Prayer.</note>MOſt gracious God, we humbly beſeech thee, to looke vpon this thy Seruant with the eyes of thy mercy: to grant him patience in his trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, comfort in his af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions, and ſtrength in thy mercies: Defend him, O Lord, from the danger of the enemy: keep him in thy protection &amp; ſaue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard: and ſend him de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuerance at thy good will and pleaſure, through Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="187" facs="tcp:12333:98"/>
Chriſt, our onely Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our and Redeemer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 22.</hi> A confeſsion to bee vſed of the ſicke by himſelfe.</head>
               <p>ALmighty and moſt mercifull Father, I acknowledge my great and grieuous offences committed againſt thy Diuine Maieſtie. I haue not (as I ought) loued thee aboue all things: I haue not ſincerely vvor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped thee: I haue not honoured thy Sacred name: I haue not ſancti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied
<pb n="188" facs="tcp:12333:99"/>
thy Sabbath: I haue not done due reuerence to my Parents and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernours: I haue borne deadly hatred: I haue li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued vnchaſtely: I haue ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken my neighbors goods: I haue depraued his good name: I haue coueted contrarie to thy comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dement: for all which, I humbly craue mercy of thee: for theſe and all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther my ſinnes known and vnknowne, which I haue committed ſince the day of my birth, I doe with an humble &amp; penitent heart, aske pardon and forgiue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of them, euen for
<pb n="189" facs="tcp:12333:99"/>
the merits of thy deare Sonne Ieſus Chriſt our onely Sauiour and Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: in whoſe name I pray, as hee himſelfe hath taught vs, ſaying: <hi>Our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther which, art in Heauen, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>O Lord Ieſus, who art the Reſurrection and the life, in whom, whoſoeuer beleeueth, ſhal not periſh, but haue life euerlaſting: I neither deſire the conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuance of this life, nor a more ſpeedy deliuerance out of this world, then ſhall ſtand with thy good will and pleaſure, to which I humbly referre my ſelfe:
<pb n="190" facs="tcp:12333:100"/>
doe with mee (moſt mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull Sauiour) according to the riches of thy good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: through thee, haue I beene holpen, euer ſince I was borne: thou art hee that tookeſt me out of my mothers wombe, and haſt preſerued mee to this houre: it grieueth me, that I haue ſo often offended thee: and I am the more grieued, that I can grieue no more then I doe, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering the grieuouſneſſe of my offences towards thee.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="23" type="chapter">
               <pb n="191" facs="tcp:12333:100"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 23.</hi> A Prayer by the ſick party a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the feare of death.</head>
               <p>O Lord, Father of mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, and God of all conſolation, heare me thy diſtreſſed creature: the feare of death is fallen vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on mee; I feare, I faint, Lord, be thou my helper. I find that death is dread<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to nature, ſhield mee vnder the ſhadow of thy wings: ſtrengthen my weakeneſſe, by thy power; my wauering, by thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; which art wont to heare and help them that
<pb n="192" facs="tcp:12333:101"/>
call vpon thee in the day of trouble: the day of trouble and heauineſſe is come vpon mee: to thee I call, in thee I truſt: though fraile fleſh begin to ſhrinke; yet grant, moſt mercifull Lord, that faith in thy moſt bleſſed Paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on may neuer decay in me: that hope may neuer faile me, but that the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable expectation of a better life to come, may reuiue &amp; raiſe vp my pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiue ſoule: when ſtrength faileth mee, and the light of mine eyes is gone: grant, Lord, that my heart may call vpon thee, and
<pb n="193" facs="tcp:12333:101"/>
ſay, <hi>Lord Ieſus, receiue my Spirit,</hi> which liueſt and reigneſt with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, one God world without end, <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 24.</hi> A Prayer for the ſicke.</head>
               <p>O Eternall God, and moſt gracious and mercifull Father, I hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly beſeech thee, to looke vpon this thy ſeruant with the eyes of mercy: ſhew him thy mercy, and grant him thy ſaluation: g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> him comfort and confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence
<pb n="194" facs="tcp:12333:102"/>
in thee, and in thy Word: ſtabliſh his heart, that his truſt may be euer in thee: impute not vnto him, his former ſinnes and offences, but couer his ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities with the righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of thy deare Sonne: defend and ſtrengthen his ſoule againſt al the aſſaults and deadly ſubtilties of our reſtleſſe enemie: de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liuer him from his tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie, and keepe him in thy protection &amp; ſauegard: draw nigh vnto his ſoule, and ſaue it: ſhew him the light of thy countenance, and bee mercifull vnto him, and ſaue him, for thy
<pb n="195" facs="tcp:12333:102"/>
mercies ſake: and ſince, O heauenly Father, thou did<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt in thy loue towards vs (euen when wee were thine enemies) giue thy moſt dearely beloued Sonne to the Death to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deeme vs: powre into his heart, I humbly beſeech thee, a true &amp; liuely faith, whereby he may take hold vpon our perfect righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſnes which is in Chriſt, and ſo bee made partaker of the merit of his Death and Reſurrection: ſuffer not the apprehenſion of death to diſcourage him: but giue him grace and courage, cheerefully to
<pb n="196" facs="tcp:12333:103"/>
attend his death; willingly to obey thy will; and pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiently to indure this thy viſitation: that after this painefull life ended, hee may dwell with thee in life euerlaſting, through the merits of thy Sonne Ieſus Chriſt our onely Sauiour and Redeemer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 25.</hi> A forme of leauing the ſicke to Gods protection.</head>
               <p>PSalme 20.1. <hi>The Lord heare thee in the day of trouble: the name of the God of</hi> Iacob <hi>defend thee, ſend
<pb n="197" facs="tcp:12333:103"/>
thee helpe from his Sanctua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, and ſtrengthen thee out of Sion:</hi> grant thee thy hearts deſire, and fulfill all thy minde. Saue (Lord) and heare vs, O King of Heauen, when wee call vpon thee. Ieſus the Son of the liuing God, put his Paſsion betweene thy ſinnes, and the Iudgement to come. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="chapter">
               <pb n="198" facs="tcp:12333:104"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 26.</hi> The manner of commending the ſicke, into the hands of God, at the houre of Death.</head>
               <p>GOd the Father, who hath created thee, preſerue and keepe thee: God the Sonne, who hath redeemed thee, aide and ſtrengthen thee: God the Holy Ghoſt, who hath ſanctified thee, aſsiſt thee in all thy tryals, and lead thee the way into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting peace. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Chriſt that dyed for thee, keep thee fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all euill.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb n="199" facs="tcp:12333:104"/>Chriſt that redeemed thee, ſtrengthen thee in all temptations.</p>
               <p>Chriſt Ieſus, that roſe from the dead, raiſe thy body and ſoule in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the iuſt.</p>
               <p>Chriſt that ſitteth at the right hand of God in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, bring thee into euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting ioy. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 27.</hi> A Prayer for the ſick, at his departing out of this life.</head>
               <p>MOſt merciful Father, we commend vnto thee, this thy Seruant the
<pb n="200" facs="tcp:12333:105"/>
work of thine own hands: wee commend vnto thee his ſoule, in the merits of Chriſt Ieſus his Redee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer: accept, O Lord, thine owne creature: for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giue, wee beſeech thee, whatſoeuer hath bin com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by humane fraile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and command thine Angels to conduct him to the land of euerlaſting peace: preſerue, O Lord, the ſoule of thy ſeruant, as thou diddeſt <hi>Lot</hi> from the fire of Sodome preſerue, O Lord, the ſoule of thy ſeruant; as thou diddeſt <hi>Daniel</hi> from the mouth of the Lyons. Into thy mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cifull
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:12333:105"/>
hands, O heauenly Father, we commend the ſoule of thy ſeruant now departing: acknowledge him, we beſeech thee, for a Sheepe of thine owne fold, and for a Lambe of thine owne flocke: re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue him into the armes of thy mercy, knowing that the thing cannot pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, which is committed to thy charge. O moſt mercifull Ieſu, receiue, we beſeech thee, his Spirit in peace. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="chapter">
               <pb n="200" facs="tcp:12333:106"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 28.</hi> The bleſsing of the ſicke, when hee is giuing vp the Ghoſt.</head>
               <p>CHriſt Ieſus abſolue thee from all thy ſins.</p>
               <p>Chriſt Ieſus, remit all the euill, that thou haſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny wayes committed.</p>
               <p>Chriſt Ieſus that dyed for thee, blot out all thy offences.</p>
               <p>Chriſt Ieſus that now calleth thee, receiue thee into his heauenly King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</p>
               <p>The Lord bleſſe thee and keepe thee: the Lord
<pb n="201" facs="tcp:12333:106"/>
make his face to ſhine vpon thee: the Lord lift vp his countenance ouer thee, and giue thee a ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Reſurrection. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Depart, O Chriſtian Soule, in the name of God the Father, who created thee: of God the Sonne, who redeemed thee: of God the Holy Ghoſt, who ſanctified thee, one liuing and immortall God, to whom bee all honour and glory, for euer and euer. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="chapter">
               <pb n="204" facs="tcp:12333:107"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 29.</hi> A Prayer to bee vſed by the aſſembly, after the ſicke mans departure.</head>
               <p>O Almighty and euer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting God, ſeeing it hath pleaſed thee to take this thy ſeruant out of the miſeries of a ſinfull world, vnto thy heauenly Kingdome: bleſſed bee thy name both now and euermore: and wee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech thee, O Lord, make vs that yet remaine, to bee mindfull of our mortali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, that wee may walke before thee in righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:12333:107"/>
and holineſſe all the dayes of our life: and when the time of our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture ſhall come, wee may reſt in thee, as our hope is, that this thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uant now doth: and that we with him, and al others departed in the faith of thy holy Name, may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioyce together in thy eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall and euerlaſting King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, through Ieſus Chriſt our Lord. <hi>Amen.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="chapter">
               <pb n="204" facs="tcp:12333:108"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 30.</hi> Conſolation againſt immode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate griefe for the loſſe of friends.</head>
               <p>TO ſorrow for the death of friends, is a dutie, by which, wee giue teſtimonie of our naturall affection: which dutie, both Chriſtianitie doth allow, and examples in holy Scripture doe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue. <hi>Abraham</hi> mourned for <hi>Sara</hi> his wife: all Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el, for <hi>Samuel</hi> the Prophet: the people in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, for <hi>Aaron</hi> their High Prieſt: the inhabitants of
<pb n="205" facs="tcp:12333:108"/>
                  <hi>Bethulia,</hi> for <hi>Iudith</hi> that Honourable Widdow: <hi>Martha</hi> and <hi>Mary</hi> for <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zarus:</hi> the twelue Patri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arkes, for <hi>Iacob</hi> their aged Father: <hi>Dauid,</hi> for <hi>Ionathan</hi> his truſtie and faithfull friend: Chriſt himſelfe (ſaith <hi>Ieremy</hi>) went not to his Sepulchre without weeping eyes: ſo that to mourne for the dead, is a thing naturall; but not to mourne at all, is againſt Nature, againſt Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, againſt all dutie. When the Apoſtle for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bade the <hi>Theſſalonians</hi> to ſorrow, hee did not abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely forbid all ſorrow,
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:12333:109"/>
but ſorrowing after the manner of the Gentiles; ſaying, <hi>Brethren, I would not haue you ignorant, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning thoſe that ſleepe, to the end you may not lament, like thoſe that haue no hope.</hi> To ſorrow as men with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope, is farre from the rule of <hi>Faith.</hi> Which tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth vs, <hi>that if we beleeue, that Ieſus Christ dyed, and was raiſed againe:</hi> in like manner, <hi>they that ſleepe in Ieſus, God will bring them vnto him.</hi> Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith, <hi>Contristamur, ſed non ſicut caetert,</hi> in deed we are ſorrowfull, but not as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers without hope. <hi>Non
<pb n="207" facs="tcp:12333:109"/>
culpamus affectum</hi> (ſaith S. <hi>Bernard) ſed exceſſum:</hi> wee blame not the affec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion it ſelfe, but the exceſſe or want of moderation: and Chriſtians, of all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who beleeue the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection vnto a better life, ſhould raiſe vp them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues from ouer-dolefull paſſions. Our Sauiour be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his paſſion, ſeeing his Diſciples ſorrowfull for his departure, ſaith vnto them, <hi>If you loued mee, you would reioyce, becauſe I ſaid, I goe vnto the Father,</hi> Ioh. 14.29. So it may be ſaid to thoſe that mourne, for the miſſe of their friends,
<pb n="208" facs="tcp:12333:110"/>
let not your minds be too much troubled, or plun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in ſorrow, becauſe they are dead, for whom you thus lament: God hath taken them vnto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe: they are gone vnto their mercifull Redeemer. Therefore as in all other things, ſo in this, a mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration ſhould be had: yet in the beſt of Gods Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, mourning hath not beene a light paſſion one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly: for great was the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that <hi>Iacob</hi> made at the ſuppoſed death of his Sonne <hi>Ioſeph,</hi> when he ſaid, <hi>I will go vnto the graue to my Sonne ſorrowing,</hi>
                  <pb n="209" facs="tcp:12333:110"/>
Gen. 50.14. Great was the lamentation that <hi>Dauid</hi> made, when newes was brought him of <hi>Abſaloms</hi> end, ſaying, <hi>O Abſalom, Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalom, my ſonne Abſalom, I would to God I had dyed for thee,</hi> 2. Sam. 1.17. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he that ſaid, <hi>My ſonne, powre forth thy teares ouer the dead,</hi> ſaid alſo, <hi>Comfort thy ſelfe.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Doth God onely lend vs one another, and ſhall we grudge when hee cals for his owne? ſhall wee thinke much to follow the example of our Sauiour, who dyed, and dyed for vs? Who can be a Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian,
<pb n="210" facs="tcp:12333:111"/>
and would not bee like him? or who can bee like him, that would not dye after him? Can wee loue our friend, and not wiſh he might be happy? and can he be happy, and not dye? Nature knowes not what ſhe would haue: we can neither abide our friends miſerable in their ſtay, nor happy in their departure: wee loue our ſelues ſo well, that we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tent, they ſhould gaine by our loſſe. If their gaine exceede our loſſe, then our mourning for them, ſhewes that we did onely loue our ſelues in
<pb n="211" facs="tcp:12333:111"/>
them: whereby our loue proues iniurious. That death is neuer to bee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plored, that is ſeconded by immortalitie. Since God then hath taken them vnto himſelfe, with whom they are now happy; let him haue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with cheere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulneſſe: ſo ſhall wee hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily with them, enioy God alſo in glory.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 31.</hi> The cuſtome of Funerals.</head>
               <p>THe cuſtome of Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals, as it is ancient, ſo is it commendable. <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi> the father of our faith,
<pb n="212" facs="tcp:12333:112"/>
purchaſed a piece of ground to bury his dead in: and in that place hee himſelfe, <hi>Sara, Iſaac, Iacob</hi> and <hi>Ioſeph</hi> were buried with great ſolemnitie and much mourning. <hi>Tobias</hi> is commended for bury<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the dead; ſo is <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> for preparing of ointment for the burying of our Sauiour: ſo is <hi>Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph</hi> and <hi>Nichodemus,</hi> for the care that they had a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Chriſts Funerall. <hi>My Sonne</hi> (ſaith the Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man) <hi>powre forth thy teares ouer the dead, and neglect not his buriall.</hi> Whence we may gather, that Fune<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
<pb n="213" facs="tcp:12333:112"/>
Rites, decent interring of the corps, exequies and ſeemely mourning, are with decencie to bee per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, as the laſt duties of loue in this world a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt friends.</p>
               <p>The cauſes of ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing of Funerals, are three:<note place="margin">Three cauſes of Funerals.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, it is the office of humanity, the duty of cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritie, decently to commit the dead corps to the earth, out of which it was taken: this charitable du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie is commended in <hi>Toby</hi> and others, and religiouſly obſerued of the very hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, it is a thing
<pb n="214" facs="tcp:12333:113"/>
very ſeemely and conue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, with reuerence to lay the corps in graue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe our bodies are the Temples of the Holy Ghoſt, which at the Day of Doome ſhall bee chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged into a condition of glorie: and by which, as by liuely inſtruments, both God hath been glorified, and his people haue recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued good: that then, which hath beene ſo notable an inſtrument, ought not to be vnreuerently intreated, though dead.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, our Faith is hereby confirmed, touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Article of our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection:
<pb n="215" facs="tcp:12333:113"/>
for <hi>we lay down the body in the earth, vnder hope, that this mortall must put on immortality,</hi> 1. Cor. 15.</p>
               <p>But Funerals are not to be vſed, thereby to relieue or benefit the the dead: for they are rather com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts to the liuing, then helpes to the dead. There commeth no part of bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſednes to the dead by Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerals; <hi>but bleſſed are they that die in the Lord. Laza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus</hi> wanted his Funerall, but the want thereof, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaued him not of his happy eſtate: hee dyed in the Lord, and ſo was bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.
<pb n="216" facs="tcp:12333:114"/>
Let vs therefore liue, as we will dye; and dye, as they that hope to riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, &amp; liue with Chriſt hereafter: for after this life, there is no helpe re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining to the dead: to the liuing, there is mercy offered: but to the dead, there remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth only iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:12333:114"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
